<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discouerie and batterie of the great fort of vnwritten traditions otherwise, an examination of the Counsell of Trent, touching the decree of Traditions. Done by Martinus Chemnitius in Latine, and translated into Englishe by R.V.</title>
            <title>Examen Concilii Tridentini. English. Selections.</title>
            <author>Chemnitz, Martin, 1522-1586.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 226KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12044</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846277_176462</idno>
  <idno type="VID">176462</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264199452</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 5116</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S110805</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99846277e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12044)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176462)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 211:07, 454:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discouerie and batterie of the great fort of vnwritten traditions otherwise, an examination of the Counsell of Trent, touching the decree of Traditions. Done by Martinus Chemnitius in Latine, and translated into Englishe by R.V.</title>
                  <title>Examen Concilii Tridentini. English. Selections.</title>
                  <author>Chemnitz, Martin, 1522-1586.</author>
                  <author>Vaux, Robert.</author>
                  <author>Cranmer, Thomas, 1489-1556. A confutation of unwritten verities.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[100] [i.e. 101], 79 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Purfoot, and William Pounsonbie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1582.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In two parts. Part 1 is an English translation by Robert Vaux from part 1 of Chemnitz, Martin.  Examen concilii Tridentini.  Part 2 is an edition of Cranmer, Thomas.  A confutation of unwritten verities (STC 5996). Register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>R.V. = Robert Vaux.</note>
                  <note>Part 2 title page (M4r) reads: A confutation of vnwritten verities ..</note>
                  <note>Part 2 title page imprint reads: Imprinted at London by Thomas Purfoote and are to be solde at his shop, without Newgate, ouer-against S. Sepulchers Churche. Anno 1582.</note>
                  <note>Running title part 1 reads: Chemnicius of traditions.</note>
                  <note>part 2 formerly also STC 5997.</note>
                  <note>part 2 identified as STC 5997 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [par.]⁴ A²  B-Y⁴ .</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Cambridge University Library (part 1 only) and the Library of Congress (part 2 only).</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 211 (Cambridge University Library; part 2 only) and at reel 454 (Library of Congress copy; part 1 only).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="meeting_name">Council of Trent (1545-1563) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176462:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176462:1"/>
            <p>¶ A Confutation of vnwritten verities, both by the holye Scriptures and most auntient authours, and also probable Arguments, and pithie reasons, with plaine aunsweres to all (or at the least) to the most part and strongest argumentes, which the Aduersa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Gods truth, either haue or can bring foorth for the proofe and defence of the same vnwritten Vanities, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities as they woulde haue them called.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Made by Thomas Cranmer, late Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of Canterburie, Martir of God, and burned at Oxen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde for the defence of the true doctrine of our Sauiour Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Contents whereof, thou shalt finde in the next side following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London by Thomas Purfoote</hi> and are to be solde at his Shop, without Newgate, ouer-against S. Sepulchers Churche.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno.</hi> 1582.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:176462:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:176462:2"/>
            <head>The Contentes.</head>
            <list>
               <item>FIrst, the preface of the Translator to his countrey men and brethren of England.</item>
               <item>Cap. 1. That the word of God, written and conteined with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Cannon of the Bible, is a true, sound, perfect, and whole doctrine, conteining in it selfe fully all things neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for our saluation.</item>
               <item>2. That the writings of the old Fathers, without th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word of God, are not able to proue any doctrine in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</item>
               <item>3. That generall Councels haue no authoritie to make new articles of our faith.</item>
               <item>4. That nothing can bee prooued by Oracles of Angles, touching religion.</item>
               <item>5. That apparicions of the deade bee vnsufficient to that purpose.</item>
               <item>6. Neither are miracles able to prooue the same.</item>
               <item>7. Custome also is of no strength in this case.</item>
               <item>8. Reasons against vnwritten verities.</item>
               <item>9. Scriptures aleaged by the Papistes for vnvvritten veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, vvith aunsvveres to the same.</item>
               <item>10. Doctors to the same purpose, vvith their aunsvveres.</item>
               <item>11. The Papistes obiections vvith ansvveres vnto them.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:176462:3"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat christian hart (dere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued countriemen and brethren, in our Sauiour Christ) can abstaine frō deepe sobbes and sorrowful sighings? What na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and kinde harted man can forbeare weeping, so ofte as hee calleth to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce the Lordes Vineyarde within the<note place="margin">Esay. 5. 2.</note> Realme of <hi>England</hi> (which he himself had of late so stronglye hedged, walled, and fenced round about, by the Princes of most famous memorie, King <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, and <hi>Edwarde</hi> the sixt, and planted therein the pure<note place="margin">Kinges and rulers ought to be ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaders, helpers and not hurters, defences and not offences to Gods people.</note> vine of his owne blessed word, by godly Preachers his Gardeners) to be so sodainly broken downe, destroyed, wasted and wrooted vp by the rootes, by the wilde Bore of the wood, and the Beasts of the field, that is, by the Romishe Bishop and his bloody ministers: and now in the same vineyarde to see planted, take roote and prosper, brambles, bryars, and hemlocks; that is, grosse ignoraunce, naughtie doctrine, false worship of God, and such other kindes of most stinking, vile and<note place="margin">Gods vvord is a svvete and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saunt grape and comforteth the hart of man to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlasting saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> filthie weedes. Oh what a sweete &amp; pleasant grape of godly doctrine was then gathered in <hi>England</hi> to the great cōfort &amp; reioising of al thē, that louingly tasted therof? Thē was Gods word (for that is the sweet and pleasaunt grape that maketh glad the hart of man) with greate freedome preached, earnestly embraced, and with greedie harts in all places receaued.</p>
            <p>Then was Gods great glorie marueilously aduaunced. Then the onely merites of Christ, then true repentaunce for our former sinnes, then trust in Gods mercie through the death of our Sauiour Christe, with a new Christian life was truely published, and preached euerye where. Then was there the common prayer rightly vsed, and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, (Baptisme I meane and the holy Communion) in suche a tongue and language set foorth, that all people mighte vnderstande them. Then were they plainely ministred without any iuggling or sorcerie, according to Christes institution, and the rule of his holye worde. Which word at that time had the price and bare the bell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way throughout the whole land.</p>
            <p>With that were all pulpets filled, Churches garnished, Printers shops
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:176462:3"/> furnished, and euerie mans house decked. With gods word was eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry<note place="margin">But the hartes of the moste parte vvere naked, bare and empty, as the profe novv alas to vvel declareth Sinne is the cause vvhy God taketh his vvord from any people.</note> mans mouth occupied, of that were all songes, enterludes, &amp; plaies made. But (alas) so long, till all was plaide vnder the boorde. But what was the cause of all this? Truly none other thing, but our owne sinnes and wickednesse. For we were talkers onely and not walkers, lippe gospellers, from the mouth outward and no farther. We were euen such, as the profite speaketh of saying: this people honoreth me with their lippes, but are farre from me with their hartes. We could speake of Gods word, and talke gloriously thereof: but in our hartes we were full of pride, malice, enuie, couetousnes, backbiting, rioting, harlot haunting, no whitte bettered at al, then we were before, vnder the Popes kingdom. Nothing was in vs amended but only our tongs, no nor they neither, if I shall speake rightly and as the truth was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede. For besides our communication of Scripture, we vsed detrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our neighboure, filthie talke, with many proud bragges of our selues. We read not the Scriptures, neather heard thē for any amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our own wicked liues: but onely to make a bragge &amp; a shew thereof, to check and to taunt others, yea and to spy small motes in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens eyes, but nothing desirous to see the great beames in oure<note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> owne. This I say (to talke and not to walke, to say and not to do) was not onely amongste the vnlearned sort: but also amongst the great clearkes and cheefe preachers of Gods worde. Whiche thing (as I iudge) was the onely cause, why God, by his iust iudgement, suffered his elect and chosen vineyard to be thus troded downe, wrooted vp, and miserably afflicted by this bloody Bore of Rome, and the fatte Buls of Basan, his cruell officers. This is the cause, why God hath suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered<note place="margin">The Pope giueth lies for truth, poi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>son for nor is hing sustenaunce, and ministreth death for life.</note> this great Antichrist to disgrace the merites of Christes passion, and in place thereof, to set vp mens merites, and in stead of his suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent satisfaction vpon the crosse once for all, to set vp his masses satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factorie for the sinnes, both of the quicke and dead.</p>
            <p>This is the cause, that this monsterous beast hath taught the inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Sayntes, and the same to bee our mediators to God, and satisfiers for our sinnes. Where as before, in the forenamed vyneyard, was planted Christe Iesus the true breade, that came downe from<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note> heauen, and that moste pure well of the water of life: now, after the<note place="margin">Iohn. 4.</note> wrooting of this monstrous and rauenous Bore, are vp sprong, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iured bread, coniured water, to driue away euill spirites, and to purge our sinnes.</p>
            <p>This bloody Bore, besides al mischeiues that he hath done to the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyard, yet ceaseth he not, with faggot, fire, &amp; al other cruell tormēts,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:176462:4"/> to constraine and compell men to worship Images, the worke of<note place="margin">Psal. 20.</note> mens handes, to knele to them, to reuerence them, to bowe to them, and with all maner of obeisaunce to honour them, cleane contrary to<note place="margin">Hie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. 10.</note> Gods commaundement, who saith: thou shalt not make to thy selfe<note place="margin">Exo. 115.</note> (muche lesse then to honoure, reuerence, and worshippe them) any grauen Image, nor the likenes of any thing that is in heauen aboue, or in the earth beneath, or in the water vnder the earth, thou shalte not bow downe to them, nor worshippe them. But yet these shamelesse wretches be not abashed to saye, that Images are necessary, because they be laie mens Bookes, teaching them, instructing them, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding<note place="margin">Gods vvord is sufficient to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct al men in he true vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of God vvithout Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</note> them to the true worshippe of God. Oh great blasphemie. Oh sacrilege. Oh spitefull robbery. What is blasphemie, what is sacrilege, what is robbery, if this be none? god giueth his word written to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery mans booke, and his pure, euerlasting and vndefiled cōmaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as sufficient instructions for al men, to the true worship of him. But these earthly wrooters (the Pope, I meane, and his Prelates) as<note place="margin">Priestes thinke themselues vvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser than God.</note> though they were wiser then God, will teache men to worship him with Images, although the same be vtterly forbiddē by God, through out the whole, course of his holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>These and suche other false and fained doctrines, contrarie to the Scriptures of God conteined in his holy Bible, are now blowne oute, blustered and yelled forth in euery pulpit. Euerye streate soundeth of these, yea euery Printers house is filled with such vngodly bagguage, yea and the same are commaunded by publique authoritie (which is much to bee lamented) to bee set foorth, and the sincere doctrine of Christes holye worde, cleane put to silence, and vtterly condemned. Neither may any man reason, or once doubte of their doctrine, vnder paine of excommunication, naye rather vnder paine of burning.</p>
            <p>And when they bee not able (as they are not able at any time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede)<note place="margin">The Pope main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine by fier and fagot▪ and not by holy scriptures. A vveake refuge if they vvere not obstinate and shamelesse.</note> to prooue any of these doctrines by the word of God written. then they flye to their vnwritten verities, that is, to certain thinges de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered (as they saye) from the Apostles by worde of mouth withoute writing. Which things are to al men vncertain: for no man knoweth certainly, what they are. But whatsoeuer pleaseth them, and maketh for theire purpose, profite, and Lordly ambicion: that is an vnwritten veritie, not to be gainesaid, or denied. This is their shot, anker, bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke, and extreme refuge, whereunto they flye, whensoeuer they are forced, and constrained by Gods worde. These they make their foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, wherevpon they build, and maintain all their superstitions, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatries and heresies. Which foundations I trust by Gods grace and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:176462:4"/> helpe so to shake, both by the open Scriptures, by the full consent of all the moste auncient writers, and by probable reasons, that the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding therevpon shal haue a fall.</p>
            <p>For this is most true, that no vnwritten veritie is, or can be necessary<note place="margin">If vnvvritten ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities vvere ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then godes vvord vvere not sufficient there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto.</note> for our saluation. For then should the sacred and holy Scriptures, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the Apostles in the spirite of God, and sealed with their bloods, seeme to be insufficient, and not able to bring vs vnto saluation. But what a great blasphemye that should bee to God and his moste holy spirite, all men (I trust) that list to read the same Scriptures, easily shall perceaue. But when these vnshamefast robbers are put to their shiftes,<note place="margin">Hierom. 7. a. Yea this is their strong tovver &amp; bulvvarke of defence: and yet vveare inoughe, not being vval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led about vvith gods vvord gods true Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the vvord Grace can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of saluation.</note> vrged and forced herein, by the open and manifest word written, then haue they another starting hole to creepe out at, crying and yelling: <hi>templum domini, templum domini, templum domini,</hi> &amp;c. the church, the church, the church, affirming in plain wordes, that the church can in no wise erre, or be deceaued. And here they disceaue themselues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they take no distinction or difference of the churche. For there are two maner of churches, one true, perfect and holy in the sighte of god, and another false, imperfect and vngodly. Truth it is▪ that the true Churche of God, being grounded, and set vpon his holy worde, (I meane the gospel of grace cannot erre vnto damnation. But the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, how shining and glorious so euer it appeare, if it wander abroad, and bee not contained within the compasse, and lymets of the worde written, is no true, but a fained and forged churche. That Church, as it<note place="margin">The church that vvandreth from Gods vvord vvritten, may and doth erre in matters of faith and saluation. Galathi. i. b.</note> is without the compasse of Gods promises made in trueth, not onelye maye but also doth commonly, yea continually erre and goe astray: for they are not couppeled to the head Chrystc, which is the life, the way and the truth. Paul the Apostle of God, and elect vessel of saluatiō, writing to the galathians, hath these words: if we (saith he) or an Angel from heauen, preach any other Gospell vnto you, then that wee haue preached, hold him accursed: and yet the papist, not fearing the curse<note place="margin">The papists feare not gods curse.</note> of God dare be bolde to teache things, which Paul neuer knewe, yea thinges cleane contrarye to his euident and manifest teaching. Such grosse Ignorance (I would to God it were but Ignorance indeed is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into their heades, and suche arrogant boldnesse possesseth their harts, that they are bold to affirme no church to be the true Church of God, but that which standeth by ordinarye succession of Bishopes, in such pōpious &amp; glorious sort, as now is seene. For if there be (say they) no such outward and visible church, how shal any man knowe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be of the Churche of Chryst, and in the right belefe, or no? To this I aunswer, that if our faith should be stayed vpon the outwarde,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:176462:5"/> glistering, and pompous church, not ruled nor gouerned by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate councell of God in his worde written: we should neuer be certaine thereof, but euer wauering and doubting, which is the gate and readie pathway to desperation, from which God defend his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen<note place="margin">Hierom. 17. Psal, 116.</note> flock. Cursed is he (sayth the scripture) that putteth his trust in mā. And why? for all men (as the Kingly Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> sayeth) are liars in their wordes, and sinners in their workes.</p>
            <p>By which wordes it appeareth playn, that there was neuer man so vertuous, so holy, nor so wel lerned, only the writers of the holy scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures<note place="margin">The general counsels haue er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and that in no smal trifles.</note> excepted, but either of ignorance, or of negligence, there esca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped some faults in his writings &amp; doings. Yea the generall Counsels thēselues also, that they make so much of, haue notably erred, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after shalbe declared. Yea such hath bin the truth of those seen chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that one general coūsel hath cōdēned another of heresie: more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, the outward seene church, wherof they brag not alittle, hath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer since the beginning any space cōtinued in the tru doctrin of god.<note place="margin">Exodus, 22.</note> Let vs begin at <hi>Moses,</hi> who was the first law giuer, &amp; we shall see the state of this outward Church, which consisteth in the ordinarie succe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssion of Bishops, whether it be so as I haue said or no. Whē <hi>Moses</hi> was gone vp to the mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> to talke with God, &amp; to receaue the Law at his handes: did not <hi>Aaron</hi> the high Priest and Bishop, with all the people, in the mean space worship the golden Calfe? read the Booke of Iudges, &amp; you shall see how the whole outward &amp; visible Churche fell to Idolatrie and worshipping of strange gods: as <hi>Baal, Astaroth,</hi> gods of the <hi>Edomites, Moabites, Philistines,</hi> and the <hi>Sirians.</hi> After the reigne of King <hi>Dauid,</hi> how many kinges were there (I pray you) in whose time false Gods were not openly worshipped? All the Kinges of Israell serued straunge gods, with the consent of the Bishops, prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes, and the whole people. And in Iuda, there passed not iij. or foure Kings after <hi>Dauid,</hi> in whose dayes open Idolatrie was not alowed &amp; practised by the consent of the Kings, Bishops, high Priestes. Scribes &amp; Pharises. Which of the Prophets did not the open &amp; visible church persecute? Where was the visible Church in the time of <hi>Elias?</hi> Were not all, that were knowne and thought to be of the Church worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of <hi>Baal:</hi> in so much that <hi>Elias</hi> thought there had bene left alyue of Gods true Churche but himselfe only? and yet notwithstanding God had preserued his Church, knowne but only to himselfe, for he<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2. 3. Reg. 22.</note> knoweth who are his. Who smote <hi>Micheas</hi> the true Prophet of God, but the chiefe Priest and Bishop <hi>Zedechias?</hi> And he, with 400 Prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes more of his own mind and religion, deceaued <hi>Achab,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised him victorie ouer the <hi>Assirians,</hi> although God had made
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:176462:5"/> them no such promise, but rather had pointed the cōtrarie, as it came<note place="margin">Hiere. 20.</note> to passe. Who commaunded <hi>Ieremy</hi> to be beaten for his true prophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sying, but <hi>Phashur</hi> the Archbishop? Who perswaded with the King that <hi>Ieremy</hi> the true Prophet of God, was a sedicious fellow, &amp; went about to discourage the people in Ierusalem, that they should not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist <hi>Nabuchodonozer</hi> King of Babilon, but the Priestes? Yea, &amp; when<note place="margin">This and such like, is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard of all true preachers and faithfull feruants of God.</note> the King deliuered him out of Prison, who but these holy men of the Church, procured him to be cast again into a deepe dongeon where they would haue famished him, if God had not put in the kings heart to take him out and deliuer him? These be the fruits &amp; practises of the visible and seene Church, which, if it be true that the Papists say, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre. But whatsoeuer they say it forceth not: for we knowe what the spiritualtie, as they cal themselues, haue ben since the beginning, the very expressed image wherof is set forth &amp; declared in the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Macha. 7. 2.</note> as they that read the story shall perceaue it well ynough, by <hi>Alcinus, Simon, Iason,</hi> and <hi>Menelaus.</hi> Now let vs come to the newe<note place="margin">Machabeorum. 4</note> testament, and see what the visible and known Church was vnder it. Who was the true Church, or howe was it knowne to the people in Christes time? The high Priestes, Bishops, Scribes, Pharises, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces, which appeared outwardly and boasted themselues to be the Church of God: were in deede, as Christ calleth them, serpents, the<note place="margin">Math. 312. 23.</note> generations of vipers, hipocrites, children of hel, painted tombes, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuters of true religion, and murtherers of the Prophets, yea of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe and his Apostles: men that shut vp the Kingdome of Heauen, so that neyther they woulde enter therein themselues, nor suffer the poore simple, that were desirous to know the truth, to enter: but excommunicated, and thrust them out of the Churche, as men cast awaye, as Heretiques, and forsaken of God, whosoeuer belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued on Christ. Who commaunded the Apostles that they shoulde<note place="margin">Act. 4. Actes. 7. Euse. ec. his. 2. 22. Act. 9. Actes 24.</note> preache no more in Christs name? Who caused <hi>Steuen</hi> to be stoned? And <hi>James</hi> to be thrown off the pinacle, who gaue authority to <hi>Paule</hi> to bind, &amp; bring before thē al that professed Christ? Who cōmaūded him to be buffeted? who accused him before <hi>Festus &amp; Agrippa?</hi> Who stirred the Gentils against him in al coūtries, where he wēt to preach, but the church? If yee will then needes iudge the outwarde visible church, that sitteth in <hi>Moses</hi> chaire (though they do not as the chaire<note place="margin">Ruffini. 1. 17.</note> requireth) to be the true church of God: I pray you then tell me, who caused <hi>Constantinus</hi> the Emperour to banish <hi>Athanasins?</hi> who exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led<note place="margin">Socrat. 6. ca. 18.</note>
               <hi>Chriostome,</hi> and many other mo godly and well learned Bishops, and slew a great number of godly &amp; wel learned men, but the Priests
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:176462:6"/> by seducing the Empresse <hi>Eudoxia?</hi> who put out the eyes of Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine<note place="margin">Cap 18.</note> the fourth Emperour and caused him to be slaine, bicause he pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Images out of the church, being worshipped contrary to gods holy wil and commaundement, but his owne mother, by the councel of the Pope and the Bishoppes, being then taken for the Church? who<note place="margin">Marke vvell the fruites of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s outvvard church and by them ye shall knovve vvhat they be.</note> deposed <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth Emperour, causing his own sonne to rebell against him? Who deposed <hi>Childericus</hi> the french King, assoiling his subiectes from their obedience to him, and made <hi>Pipine</hi> King in his steade, but the Pope and his Church men? Let vs come to our owne realme and speake of thinges done in our owne memory. Who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured Kinge <hi>Henry</hi> the eyght in the beginning of his reigne to warre against the french King, where besides the murther committed, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie was learned, theft and sacrilege practised, lying, swearing, yea and forswering with al other kindes of vices vsed, which be the very fruites of war, but the Clergi? For the Pope, then being in war with the french King, to make his part good and the stronger, procured the Bishopps of the Church of <hi>England</hi> being the Popes deare darlinges, and chiefe of the kinges councel to entitle the king to his right of the realme and crowne of <hi>France:</hi> and to encourage the young King thereto, the Pope accursed the king of Fraunce and al his aiders and succourreres. Then free pardons flue abroade as thick as butter flies in summer: but so free, that the realme thereby and the said warriers was robbed of a<note place="margin">The pope ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth himselfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to God yea rather aboue him in this his promise.</note> great deale of our Treasure, and in manner halfe vndone. There was ful remission a <hi>penae</hi> and <hi>culpa</hi> preached at <hi>Paules crosse,</hi> and almost in euery sermon, through all <hi>England:</hi> promising that whosoeuer dyed in the Popes quarell, his soule should bee in heauen before his bones were cold. After when the same King Henry had iustly by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Gods worde, and the ful consent both of the parliment, and Conuocation, abolished the vsurped power of the Bishop of <hi>Rome:</hi> then the Pope interdited the whole Realme, and sent Cardinall <hi>Poole</hi>
               <note place="margin">This is one of the practises of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates.</note> from prince to prince, to excite and moue them (if he coulde haue broughte it to passe) to make open warre againste the Kinge and the realme, as it appeareth in a Sermon preached by <hi>Tonstall</hi> then Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of <hi>Durham</hi> and set out in printe openly.</p>
            <p>Which sermon and all other tel truthes, openinge the abuses and tiranie of the Bishop of Rome, are now put to silence. Who were the worker of all these mischeifes? who these. iij. yeares past, hath perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, prisoned, and burned so many learned and Godly men, onely for their true faythes sake grounded vpon Gods most holy worde (men worthy to bee compared with the olde martirs of the primitiue
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:176462:6"/> church as well for the constancy of their faith, as also for pacience and charity shewed at their deathes) but the church, as they call thēselues?<note place="margin">The spirituall man neuer perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuteth the carnal man, but forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him. Hier. Gala. 4.</note> who by their cruell tiranie, hath enforsed so many notable mēbers of Christ, (leauing wife, children, kinsfolke, Lands and goodes) either to flye into strange realmes, or else from towne to towne, from Citie to Citie: onely because they woulde not drinke of the venemous cup of the whore of <hi>Babilon?</hi> who hath wrought all these wickednesses, but onely the mitered Prelates and their Popishe priestes? If we shall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe them for the true Church of God, that appeare to be the visible and outward Church, consisting of the ordinary successiō of Bishops:<note place="margin">Exo. 12. 1. Pet.</note> then shall we make Christ, which is an innocent lambe without spot, and in whome is foūd no guile, to be the head of vngodly and disobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient members. Which thing is as impossible, as to make God, which is onely good, and nothing but goodnesse it selfe to be the authour, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal, and cause of all euill. For Christ, as he is pure, holy and perfite, euen so must his Church and members be, to whome he (as the head)<note place="margin">Eph. 1. Collos. 1.</note> is adioyned and coupled. But if we alowe the Pope, his Cardinalles, Bishops, priests, Monks, Canons, Friers &amp; the whole rable of the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, to be this perfect Church of God, whose doinges are cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary (for the moste part) to the will, and commaundement of Christ, left and expressed in his word written: then make we him a sinner, and his word of no effect. For as sweete agreeth with sower, blacke with white, darknesse with light, and euil wtth good: euen so this outward, seene and visible Church, consisting of the ordinary succession of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, agreeth with Christ. But here they. will aske me, howe shall a man know whether he be in the right faith, but by this Church? To this Christ shal make answere himselfe, saying in the Gospel of Iohn, my sheepe heare my voice, and shall not here a straunger. And where<note place="margin">Iohn. 1</note> (I pray you) hath Christ left any voyce to bee heard or folowed, but in his word written? Search the Scriptures, saith he: for they beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.</note> of me. Where he biddeth you not to searche vnwritten verities, such as the outward, seene and pompeous Church shall of their owne<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note> heades shew you, but the written verities, conteined in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which are profitable to teache, to improue, to amend, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct in righteousnesse, that the man of God may be perfect and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared vnto al good workes.</p>
            <p>If thou therefore be desyrous to knowe whether thou be in the righte faith or no, seeke it not at mans mouth: for all men bee lyers. Seeke it not (I saye) at a proude, gloryous, and waueringe sorte of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, and Priestes: but at Gods owne mouth, which is his holye
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:176462:7"/> word written, which can neither lye, deceaue, nor be disceaued. Aske<note place="margin">Psa. 116. Gods vvord one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly certifieth a man vvhether his faith be good or no.</note> (I say) seke, and knock by diligent study, and earnest praier vnto God, who hath promised to giue to al them, that aske faithfully of him the certaintie of good faith in their conscience, taught and confirmed by the holy Scriptures of the old and new Testament. And here I forbid no man as though they should not aske and learne of the learned: for that is good and necessary, yea and alowed by Gods trueth, but this would I haue all men to doe, to vse discretion, and wisedome in this<note place="margin">Try euery spirite but alovv none further then they agree vvith the vvritten Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Gods vvord trieth al thinges vvhether they be good or badde.</note> matter: and to know whether they be learned, godlye minded, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to instruct by the Scriptures or no. And yet if they be, beleeue them no further, then they can shew their doctrine and exhortation to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable with the true word of God written. For that is the very touch stone, which must, yea and also wil, try all doctrine or learning what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer it be, whether it be good or euil, true or false. And let not men of small learning be to curious in asking or mouing darke and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full questions, which breede contention rather then Godly edifying, but let them be content with the plaine and open places of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Let them rather be earnest to obserue the commaundementes of faith and loue, which are plainly set foorth in Gods booke, then to trouble themselues, and busie their heades with darke places: for that is a thing that hath done, and also doeth displease God verye greatly. Yea I thinke surely, that these heauy plagues, wherewith God moste iustly punisheth now this realme of England (which I beseeche him of his infinite mercie either to take clean away, or else to mittigate thē for his elect sake) commeth not so much for the simple, innocent, and vnlearned sorte, which being beguiled through their simplicitie, by the craft and subtyltie of the wylie Papistes, doe still continue in su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition and Idolatrie: but rather for the curious sort, which preache straunge and farre fetched doctrines, nothing so much to edifying as to contentious brawling. Yea I would to God there were not a great number of them, that were and are counted learned, which preache and defend doctrines, which themselues know to be vntrue, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the euident Scriptures. Would God there were not many hundreds of great gospellers sometimes, that had not subscribed with their owne hands and confirmed by their open and publique Sermōs, the contrary of that, which they once builded in Christ. And some of<note place="margin">Their conciences shall therefore condemne them for so doing, if they repent not in time.</note> such (I know) in perswading priuately with their old freinds, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintaince, haue confessed no lesse, but that they haue done contrary to the truth, and the good perswasion of their own conscience: and yet the same men councell their freinds for vnytie and peace sake (as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:176462:7"/> they terme it) but rather they may say for feare of losse of goodes and life to obay wicked superstition, naughtie rites and damnable lawes. But what peace, or what vnity is that, that is against god &amp; his Christ? And what profiteth it a man to winne al the world and loose his own<note place="margin">Math. 16.</note> soule, for he that loueth his own life more then me (saith Christ) is not worthy of me. For these mēs sakes therfore, that is to say, the stubborn Papists, that lead the world in blindnesse, cōtrary to their own consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences:<note place="margin">The vvitte and vertue of delicate gospellers is in their tongues.</note> and specially for delicate gospellers sakes, whose wit &amp; vertue is in their tongs, whot disputers, busie talkers, taunters &amp; fault finders with others, rather then mēders of thēselues: for these two sorts sakes chefely (I say) God heapeth these great plagues, that is persecution of his word, dearth, daunger of war and people of strange nations, likely to subdue and vtterly distroy that our realme, except they repent, &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēd their liues in time, and become not only forgetful of their former euils: but also diligēt workers and true folowers of the word, that they haue so lightly condemned, and refused. Which if they doe not, let them be sure, that all the plagues which are written in the booke of God, and all the blood of his saintes, which hath bene shed from iust Habel vnto this present time, shall be poured vpon them. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer<note place="margin">Math. 23.</note> these men doe, let vs (deare brethren) whose hartes God of his goodnesse hath more mercyfully touched, repent and amend our former liues, and ceasse from all dead workes, least we be partakers of the same plagues with them. But thankes be vnto our God, that hath so gently ordered vs, for this we know, that God suffereth not his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple long to followe their owne mindes: but shortly punisheth them, which is a token of his great louing kindnesse toward them. For this<note place="margin">2. Mach. 6.</note> grace haue we of God more then other people (as it is written) that he suffreth not vs long to sinne vnpunished like other nations, that when the day of Iudgement commeth, he may punishe them in the fulnesse of their sinnes.</p>
            <p>If we sinne he correcteth vs, but hee neuer withdraweth his mercy from vs, and though he punishe vs with aduersitie, yet doth he neuer forsake his people. For whome (as Paule sayth) the Lord loueth, him<note place="margin">Ebru. 12.</note> he chasteneth: yea and he scourgeth euery sonne whom he receaueth. But to leaue this digression and come to our purpose agayne: I will breefely shewe you, what the outward face of the Church and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath bene in all ages, euen such as hath pleased the mightie kings,<note place="margin">2. Para. 13.</note> Emperours, and rulers of the world when <hi>Jeroboam</hi> set vp the golden Calues at <hi>Bethel</hi> and <hi>Dan,</hi> the Priestes and Leuites consented thereto, and all Israel worshipped them contrary to Gods commaundement.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:176462:8"/> When <hi>Jesabel</hi> had perswaded with her husbande about murther, he<note place="margin">The vvill of a vvoman must be folovved, or else a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l the fat is in the fire.</note> fulfilled her mind &amp; slew all the Prophets of God, that he could come by, only <hi>Elias</hi> remained, that was known to be the true church, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Priests of <hi>Baal</hi> were 450 in number. <hi>Ezechias</hi> destroyed the brasen serpent and restored the true religion and worship of God: but <hi>Manasses,</hi> his sonne set vp Idolatrie, maintained wicked religion, and slue them that were good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sias</hi> restored right Religion: but <hi>Iehoas</hi> and <hi>Jehoachim,</hi> his sonnes<note place="margin">4. Re. 23. 4. Re. 24.</note> forsooke it, and all their Priests and subiects with them cōmitted Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie.<note place="margin">As Princes vvold so al things vvere done.</note> And generally, what religion soeuer the king would haue, that was stablished for his time: so that (as <hi>Salomon</hi> sayth of the Iudges) so may we say of the Cleargie: whatsoeuer sayth the Prince, that sayth the Priest. But let vs once agayn come to the new testament. Did not<note place="margin">Math. 26. Math. 27.</note> the head Rulers of the Church, with the authoritie of <hi>Herode</hi> &amp; <hi>Pilate</hi> condemn Christ &amp; his doctrine as erronious and sedicious: and al the people followed and cried <hi>Crucifige?</hi> did not all the Emperors before <hi>Constantine,</hi> being seduced by their Bishops and Priestes, condemne Christiā religion as hereticall, sedicious, and traiterous, &amp; for the same murthered many thousands of Martirs? When <hi>Constantine</hi> was chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stened, then was the true religion first set forth &amp; openly preached by publique authoritie: and yet in the space betweene Christ and this godly Emperor, God was not without his church, though it were not known, seen, and so accepted of the world. In this Princes time, &amp; by his authoritie, was kept the first &amp; best general coūcell of Nice, where was set foorth our common Creede, containing shortly the cheefe &amp; most necessary articles of our beleefe. This <hi>Constantinus</hi> sonne, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantius,</hi> fauouring the errour of the <hi>Arrians,</hi> in the councell of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theodoriti. lib. 2 cap 18.</note> decreede that Christ was not God but man only.</p>
            <p>And then to call Christ the sonne of God, was by the outwarde known church, and by a generall councell condemned for an hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous heresie. From that time foorth whē Painime Princes reigned, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie and worshipping of false Gods was the publique doctrine,<note place="margin">The priestes for the most part vvere double fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, turne tippets and flatterers.</note> Whē hereticks reigned &amp; bare the rule, heresie was openly preached for Gods truth. When the Emperors were Catholicke, then was the true doctrine of the Gospell openly preached. And generally such as was the faith of the Emperors, kings, or other rulers, such did the Prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes preach. And if any by the authoritie of gods worde preached the contrary, or withstood their corrupt teachings, straight waye he was either deposed from his office, condemned for an heretick, banished, brent, or put to some other cruell death. After all these sprong vp the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:176462:8"/> Pope, that triple crowned monster and great Antichrist, which toke vpon him authoritie, not only ouer the Cleargie, but also clymed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue Kinges and Emperours deposing them at his pleasure, and set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led himself in the temple of God, that is, in the cōsciences of men, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolling himself aboue God, dispensing with good lawes, and giuing men leaue to breake them, and to regard more his decrees, thē the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlasting commaundments of God. And so it came to passe in time, that to eate flesh on the Friday or fastingday, was counted greater sin thē dronkēnesse, adultrie or periury. And why, because his lawes were diligētlier &amp; more straightly looked too, &amp; the offenders therof sorer punished, thē Gods lawes. Since this Antichrist of Rome (I saye) was stablished in his full power, whatsoeuer pleased him, that was takē for gods law, and that was decreede vpon by generall councell, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, &amp; ratified by whole heapes of clearkes. To speake against that was, and also now is detestable heresie, &amp; so hainous a crime against the holy Ghost (if it were true that they say) that it cannot be forgiuen either in this world, or in the world to come. He that speaketh against any of his decrees, must vtterly be condemned for an Heretique, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cursed<note place="margin">These be the popes thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolts vvhervvith he feareth the people, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to his vvaies.</note> of God, and damned into hell for euer without redemption: except he recant, abiure, and denie the truth, and set foorth error and false doctrine, and promise with a solemne Oath, that hee shall neuer preache, teache, nor defend the truth hereafter. Now let vs come to our dayes. When King <hi>Henrie</hi> the viij. was (as he ought to be by gods law) made supreme head, as well of the Cleargie as of the Laitie: he, by the consent of the parliament and conuocation, set foorth in print a godly booke of Religion, not much varying from that, whiche was enacted in his sonnes time <hi>Edward</hi> the sixt.</p>
            <p>But when he tooke displeasure with certayne Bishops (as they<note place="margin">It vvas a small matter at that time to be disple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vvith such men, and so much the more for that they vvithstoode priuate commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie.</note> tearme them) of the new learning, because they woulde not giue their consent in the parliament, that the King should haue all Abbye landes to his owne vse: but onely suche landes as were giuen by his Aunceters kinges of <hi>Englande,</hi> and that the residue of those landes should haue bene bestowed to augment the number of learned men in the vniuersities, to the founding also of Grammer Schooles in euery shire of <hi>Englande,</hi> where children (most apt to learning) should haue bene broughte vp freelye, and withoute greate coste to their friendes and kinsfolkes: to the founding of hospitals where poore and impotent people should haue bin sufficiently prouided for, with phisitions and Surgeons, which should haue ministred phisicke and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:176462:9"/> surgerie freely, not only to them, but also to all other poore folk, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Realme: and also in euery shire towne, &amp; other market towns, where should be thought most meet and fit, to set vp diuers occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (most ptofitable for the common wealth) where al valiaunt and sturdie beggers should haue bene set to worke, and if they refused to labour, then to force them thereto by whipping, stocking, and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: and the residue of the Abbie Landes aboue these, should haue<note place="margin">Priuate commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, and popish suttilty ouercame good publike po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie and brought in tiranie.</note> bene reserued in the common treasuries, to ayde the king in his wars or other affaires of his Realme, and thereby to haue fauoured and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the more his subiectes in taxes, subsidies, fifteenths, and lones, and such other like thing: King <hi>Henrie</hi> (as I said before) vpon the displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure taken, and by the incitation of the olde Popish Bishops, shortlye after (by consent of the same, or the most part of them, that were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the first booke of religion) set forth by open parliament and conuocation the sixe articles, as wel agreeing with the former parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the word of God, as black with white, light with darknesse, Christ with Belial, or with Antichrist. But after, when he was pacified with these foresayd Bishops, considering that they spake agaynst the kinges profite not of malice, but of good conscience, and zeale to Gods glorie and the common wealth, he mitigated the sixe articles, and from that time foorth, more and more, restored true religiō. And I doubt not but if he had liued, he woulde haue brought all thinges to a better state, thē he left it. But <hi>Edward</hi> the sixt his sonne (succeeding in his said fathers place, by the aduise of his vncle the Duke of Somer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set, the Lordes of his Councell, Bishops and the Cleargie) set foorth such a Booke of Religion, as (without boast or disprayse of other be it spoken) was neuer a better sette forth since the Apostles tyme.</p>
            <p>Now, after that God had plagued this realm with the most greuous<note place="margin">They are al periu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, so many as gaue their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Rome, the Bishopes, I vvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt you vvere none of those: for they cannot erre. these are vvaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring reedes, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perfect vveather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cockes, that turne vvith eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vvinde.</note> plague that euer came to it, in taking awaye from it, so godly a King as he was, yea such a one as hath not been read of, of his age, in any Realme, both for wit, learning, sobernesse and godlinesse: in his stead he hath set vp Queene <hi>Marie,</hi> who in short time hath pulled down, that was not builded in manye yeares, and brought in the Bishop of Rome, before iustly and by law of parliament abolished, with open periurie of so many, as gaue their voices and consent to the same. For they had all made a solemne othe before, neuer to receaue his vniust vsurped power into the Realme againe.</p>
            <p>Hath she not (being seduced by the periured Prelacies) reuoked and made of none effect, so many godly lawes enacted by parliamēt, that is, by the consent of the Lordes both spirituall and temporal, the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:176462:9"/> Cleargie and common house: yea and by them, that were the chiefe<note place="margin">By their deedes ye shall knovve them, vvhat they be.</note> of King Henrie her Fathers priuie counsell, and setters on of him in the abolishing of the Bishop of Rome, euen open preachers, and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, against the Popes tirannie, with so pithie reasons and strong ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentes: as neither they themselues, nor any other after them, shall be able at any time rightly to assoyle and aunswere? Yet these men were chiefe of counsell, and procurers of the Queene, and first wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers in the Parliament to alure the Lordes and commons, to receaue the Bishop of Rome againe for the supreme heade of this Realme, contrarie to Gods law, the lawes of this Realme, and their owne so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne othes. And not only this, but they haue taken away the actes of mortmaine, and premunire, and diuerse other statutes that did bridle the vnsatiate couetousnesse and licencious libertie of the Popishe Priests, and restored the Acte <hi>ex officio.</hi> Which thing if it should long continue in this state that it is in, the great treasure of this Realm should come into the Cleargies hands, and a great part therof should flie to Rome for Bishoprickes, Benefices, Appellacions, pardons, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensations and suche other bagguage. But (saye the Papistes) when Scriptures be harde and doubtful, and seeme to be contrary one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother by mistaking and wrong vnderstanding, whereof diuerse he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies doe arise: how shall a man knowe the truth in such diuersity of<note place="margin">In his. 3. booke of Christian doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine cap. 18. In his. 2. booke of Christian doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. Cap. 9. In his. 2. booke of merites and forgiuenesse of sinnes. Rom. 7. Cap. vlti.</note> opinions both parties grounding themselues vppon the Scriptures, but onely by the Church, which (as they saye) cannot erre? S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> shall make aunswere herein for me, saying on this wise: darke places are to be expounded by more plain places, for that is the surest way of declaring the Scriptures to expound one Scripture by another. And again he saith that in things openly conteined in the Scriptures, are found all things that concerne faith good liuing and charity. And if any thing cannot be tried by the certaine and cleare places of the Scriptures, let mans presumption (saith he) stay it selfe, not leaning to either part: for this I am sure of, if that it were requisite to be known vpon pain of damnation, their should not lacke most plain and cleare authorities of the same in the Scriptures. But in seeking of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, let vs seek no farther then is left in writing by God our sauiour, least in desiring to much, we leese all. S. <hi>Crisoctom</hi> also saith: it is not<note place="margin">Vpon Genesis Cap. 14. Hom. 35.</note> possible, that he, which with earnest studye, and feruent desire, apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him to the Scriptures of God, should euer be neglected of God, but althoughe we lacke a maister to teache vs: yet the Lord himselfe, entering oure hartes from aboue, shall geue light into our mindes, and poure his bright beames into our reason and vnderstanding, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:176462:10"/> open the thinges that be hid, and teache vs those tringes whereof we be ignorant. Therefore (saith the same <hi>Chrisostom</hi>) if thou wilt enter<note place="margin">In his vnperfecte vvorke. Gapb 23.</note> into the truth of the Scriptures, now aske by prayers, now knocke by good workes, and search the old auncient writers, and aske diuerse priestes, to knowe which be the true keye keepers, and which are the false.. For all thinges (saith he) are plaine, and manifest in the deuine Scriptures, whatsoeuer thinges are needefull are there opened. But if these authours will not satisfie them, then let them vse S. <hi>Iames</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell,<note place="margin">Iacob. 1.</note> saying: he that lacketh wisedom, let him aske it of God, which giueth to al men indifferently, and casteth no man in the teeth, and it shalbe giuen him. For God is not partiall, nor regardeth any more a Pope then a Potter, a Cardinal then a carter, a Bishop then a Butcher, a Prieste then a Pedler, except his faith and life be agreeable to Gods will.</p>
            <p>Whether should a man (desiring to know the truth, and right vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding and worshipping of God) haue resorted to <hi>Elias</hi> his time when there was no more of the true outward Church: but he alone? To whom should a man haue resorted for counsell of the truth, in the time of <hi>Jeremie?</hi> Of whome should a man haue learned the truth in Christes tyme, when there was no ordinarie succession of Bishops in the truth? Should they haue learned (think you) the truth of God of the head Priests, Scribes and Pharisies? Then you know, what a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning they should haue had, and how much Christ should haue profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them. Howe should a man haue bene satisfied of his saluation at <hi>Annas, Caiphas</hi> and the rest of the Pharises hands? Euen so no doubt would they haue taught &amp; instructed him, that if he had beleued and folowed their sayinges, Christ and he should neuer haue met. And yet those men bare the Image and name of the knowne Church at that time, yea and the same men condemned him of whome our faith and saluation depēdeth, as a seditious felow, as a traitor to <hi>Caesar,</hi> as an hereticke, and a blasphemer of God. Christ therefore, to teach vs what we should doe in matters pertaining to his glory and our owne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, sendeth his hearers to the Scriptures, and not to the Church, he said also to the <hi>Saduces,</hi> ye erre because ye know not the scriptures,<note place="margin">Math. 22. Mark. 12.</note> and not because ye beleeue not the Church. He also promiseth his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, that they shall heare his voice and not a straungers voyce. If ye be<note place="margin">Ioan. 10.</note> doubtful therfore in any point, resort to the Scriptures giuen from god, and out of them search for the thing whereof thou art ignoraunt, and aboue all things be not to rashe in iudgment, neither ttust to much in thine owne witte.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:176462:10"/>
            <p>Aske also counsell of such men, whome thou knowest to bee well▪ learned and exercised in the same Scriptures, and whose conuersati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thou seest to be agreeable to their words: and yet beleue them no farther, then they can proue their doctrines and exhortations to ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were, &amp; agree with god his most holy word. Seke, aske, cry, cal, knock, fast and pray, with a constant faith, ioyning thereto a Christian, sober, and a charitable liuing: and then he, that hath the keye of <hi>Dauid,</hi> who<note place="margin">Apo. 3.</note> openeth and no man shutteth, shall (according to his promise) geue vnto you all that you aske of his father in his name, and shall send his<note place="margin">Iohn. 15.</note> holy spirite into your hartes: who shall lead you into all truth and put you in remembraunce of all those thinges, which Christ hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, needefull and necessary for your saluation. Whatsoeuer therefore the Churche teacheth you out of the Canonicall bookes of the Bible, beleue that: but if they teach any thing beside that (I meane which is not agreable with the same) beleue neither that, nor thē. For then they are not the Church of Christ but the Sinagog of Sathan &amp; Antichrist. For the Church of God (as S. <hi>Paule</hi> witnesseth) is builded<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.</note> vpō the foūdation of the Apostles &amp; Prophetes, not vpō the Apostles, but vpon the same foundation, which they laid, that is, Christ Iesus, &amp; his holy word. And all such vnwritten verities, as the Papistes haue in their mouthes, though they seeme neuer so glorious a Church to the face of the world, if they be not agreeing (as they are not indeede) to the very word of God, suspect them: yea rather I bid you vtterly to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre and reiect them. For their outward and seene Church may and doth (as is before prooued) cōmonly erre in great and waighty mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Stand fast therefore to sound and good doctrine, and wauer not. And if any man come vnto you and bring not this doctrine with him,<note place="margin">2. Iohn epistle. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> receaue him not into youre house: bid him not godspeede: nor haue ought to doe with him: but count him as an abiecte from God and Christ. But cleaue ye fast to the sounde and certaine doctrine of Gods infallible word, written in the Canonicall bookes of the new and old testament, which is able sufficientlye to instruct you to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall saluation through Iesus Christ our Lorde. To whom with the Father, and the holy Ghost, bee all honoure and prayse for euer and euer. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="book_to_the_reader">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:176462:11"/>
            <head>The Booke to the Reader.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>IƲdge not before.</l>
               <l>Thou know mine intent,</l>
               <l>But reade me throughout,</l>
               <l>And then say thy fill:</l>
               <l>As thou in opinion</l>
               <l>Art minded and bent,</l>
               <l>Whether it be</l>
               <l>Either good or ill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I care for praise,</l>
               <l>Nor slaunder vntrue,</l>
               <l>Of man nor of childe,</l>
               <l>What euer he be:</l>
               <l>Truth neede not to feare</l>
               <l>Who doth it pursue,</l>
               <l>With praise or dispraise</l>
               <l>In any degree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For truth is not bettered</l>
               <l>By prayses at all,</l>
               <l>Nor harmed by dispraise</l>
               <l>Of any wight:</l>
               <l>But goodnesse or hurt</l>
               <l>Most surely come shall,</l>
               <l>To him that doth iudge</l>
               <l>Either wrong or right.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Reade me, then iudge me,</l>
               <l>Therefore, I thee pray,</l>
               <l>Nothing for my cause,</l>
               <l>But only thine own:</l>
               <l>For I shall indure,</l>
               <l>Whosoeuer say nay,</l>
               <l>When vnwritten truths</l>
               <l>Shall be ouerthrown.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:176462:11"/>
            <head>A Confutation of Vnwritten Ʋerities, by diuerse aucthorities, diligently and truely gathered togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, out of the holy Scriptures and aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient fathers.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>That the word of God written, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned within the Canon of the Bible, is a true, sound, perfect and whole doctrine, containing in it selfe fully, all thinges needefull for our saluation. The first Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>E shall put nothing to the worde, which I commaunde you, neither take oughte therfrom: that ye may keepe the commaūdements of the<note place="margin">Deut. 4.</note> Lord your God, which I command you.</p>
               <p>You shal not doe atfer any thing, that we do here this day, euery man what semeth him good in his own<note place="margin">Deut. 12.</note> eyes.</p>
               <p>Whatsoeuer I commaund you, that take heede you doe only to the<note place="margin">Ibidem. in fine▪</note> Lorde, and put nothing thereto nor take ought therefrom.</p>
               <p>The Prophet, which shall presume to speake a word in my name,<note place="margin">Deu. 18.</note> which I haue not commaunded him to speake, or that speaketh in the name of straunge gods, that Prophet shall die.</p>
               <p>All the wordes of God are pure and cleane: for he is a shield vnto<note place="margin">Pro. 30.</note> all them that put their trust in him. Put thou nothing vnto his wordes, least he reprooue thee, and thou be found a lyar.</p>
               <p>Heare not the wordes of the Prophets, that preache vnto you and<note place="margin">Iere. 23.</note> deceaue you: for they speake the meaning of their own harts, &amp; not out of the mouth of the Lorde.</p>
               <p>Whosoeuer teacheth &amp; keepeth the same (speaking of his cōmaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements)<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:176462:12"/> shall be called great in the Kingdome of heauen.</p>
               <p>Whosoeuer heareth these my wordes, and doth the same, shall be<note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> likened vnto a wise man, that buildeth his house vpon a rock: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundaunce of raine fell, the floods came, the winde blew, and beat vpon the same house, and it fell not, because it was grounded on the sure rock.</p>
               <p>This people draweth nie vnto me with their mouth and honoureth<note place="margin">Math. 15.</note> me with their lips, howbeit their harts be far from me, but in vaine do they serue me, teaching the doctrines and preceptes of men.</p>
               <p>Go ye, and teache all nations, baptizing them in the name of the<note place="margin">Math. 28.</note> father, &amp;c. teaching them to obserue all thinges whatsoeuer I haue commaunded you.</p>
               <p>Goe yee into all the world, and preache my Gospell to all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.<note place="margin">Mark. 16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>He that heareth my worde, and beleeueth in him that sent me, hath<note place="margin">Iohn, 5.</note> euerlasting life, and shall not come into damnation: but is escaped frō death to life.</p>
               <p>Search the Scriptures, for in them ye think ye haue eternall life, and<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.</note> they are they which testifie of me.</p>
               <p>These are written that you might beleeue, that Iesus is Christ the<note place="margin">Iohn. 20.</note> sonne of God, and that (in beleeuing) yee mighte haue life thorow his name.</p>
               <p>I haue spared no labour, but I haue shewed you all the Councell of<note place="margin">Actes. 20.</note> God.</p>
               <p>I haue obtained helpe of God, and continue vnto this day, witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing<note place="margin">Acte. 26.</note> both to the smal and to the great, saying none other thinges, then those which the Prophets and <hi>Moses</hi> did say should come.</p>
               <p>Fayth commeth by hearing, hearing commeth by the worde of<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> God.</p>
               <p>Whatsoeuer is not of Faith, the same is sinne.<note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Wee bee not Lordes ouer your Faith: but helpers of your ioye.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1. Gala. 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Though we our selues, or an Aungell from Heauen, preache any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gospell vnto you, then that which we haue preached, let him be accursed.</p>
               <p>Continue thou in the thinges, which thou hast learned, which also<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note> were cōmitted vnto thee, knowing of whom thou hast learned them. and for as much also as thou hast known the holy scriptures of a child which are able to make the learned vnto saluation, through the fayth, which is in Christ Iesu. For al scripture, giuen by inspiracion of God, is profitable to teache, to improoue, to amend, to instruct in righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:176462:12"/> that the man of God may be perfecte, and prepared to all good workes.</p>
               <p>If any man speake, let him speake as the wordes of God.<note place="margin">1. Pete. 4. 2. Iohn, epistle.</note>
               </p>
               <p>If any man come vnto you, and bring not this learning, receaue him not into your house, neither bid him God speede. For he, that biddeth him God speede, is partaker of his euill deedes.</p>
               <p>If any man shall adde vnto these thinges, God shal adde vnto him<note place="margin">Apo. 22.</note> the plagues, that are written in this booke. And if any man shall mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish of the wordes of this prophesie, God shall take away his part out of the booke of life, and out of the holy citie, and from those thinges, which are written in this booke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>That the writings of the old Fathers, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the written word of God, are not able to prooue any doctrine in Religion, Cap. 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
                  <hi>Renaeus lib. 2. cap.</hi> 46. To leane to the Scriptures of<note place="margin">Doctrine in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, must be grounded vpon the Scriptures onely.</note> God (which is the certaine and vndoubted truth) is to build a mans house vpon a sure and strong rock: But to leaue that, and leane to any other doctrines (whatsoeuer they be) is to build a ruinous house vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the shattering grauell, whereof the ouerthrow is easie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Idem in Epist.</hi> 72. Happy is he that soweth vpon the water where<note place="margin">VVe may not build our faith vpon mens Tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ditions.</note> the Oxe and the Asse treadeth, that is, vpon that people which onely followeth the doctrine of both the testaments, and not vpon the vayn traditions of men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> in the prescriptions of Hereticks, pa. 19. It is not lawfull for vs to fauour any doctrine at our pleasure, nor yet to chose what a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man hath brought in of his owne minde.</p>
               <p>We haue the Apostles of the Lord for our authours, which did not<note place="margin">The Apostles taught nothing but that, vvhich they learned of Christ.</note> elect any thing (that they would bring in) of their owne heades: but taught, faithfully to all nations, that doctrine, that they had receyued of Christ.</p>
               <p>Therefore although an Aungell from heauen, shoulde preache any other thing, let vs hold him accursed.</p>
               <p>And a little after he sayth. We neede to vse no curiositie after Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus<note place="margin">The first poynt of beleefe is, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the gospel no other thing is to be beleeued.</note> Christ, nor make farther searche after the Gospell: for when wee
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:176462:13"/> beleeue, we desire to beleeue no more. For first we beleeue this, that there is nothing else that we ought to beleeue.</p>
               <p>Idem of the flesh of Christ, pa. 20. against <hi>Apelles</hi> which sayde that<note place="margin">There is no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenty in that the scripture defineth not.</note> the Aungels had a bodily substaunce, which they tooke of the sterres. <hi>Tertullian</hi> answereth, that there is no certaintie in this matter, because<note place="margin">The lavve, the Prophetes, and Gospel, are the first doctrines, and therefore true.</note> the scripture declareth it not.</p>
               <p>The same to <hi>Praxeas.</hi> Let this be a generall rule, indifferently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined before hand against al heresies, that that is true, whatsoeuer is first: and that to be forged, whatsoeuer commeth after. pa. 418.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Origen</hi> in his first homilie vpon <hi>Ieremy.</hi> We must needes call the<note place="margin">Our vvordes, vvith Gods vvordes, are not to be beleeued.</note> holy Scriptures to witnesse: for our iudgements and expositions with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out these witnesses, are worthie no credite.</p>
               <p>Idem vpon <hi>Leuiticus,</hi> in his fist homilie. If the holy scripture do not<note place="margin">That vvhich can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be prooued by the Scripture, leaue to God.</note> determin any thing, we ought not to admit any other writing, for the stablishing of our doctrine: but as for the rest, let vs leaue it to God.</p>
               <p>The same vpon the third chapter to the <hi>Romanes.</hi> After these as his custome is (meaning by S. Paule) he doth confirme, that he had sayde by the scriptures, giuing also an example to the Preachers of the church that those thinges, which they speake to the people, shoulde be armed and maintained by the holy Scriptures, and not spoken out of their owne iudgementes. For if he, (being such and so great an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle) thought not the authoritie of his own wordes to be sufficient, except he teach those things, which he sayth, to be written in the law and the Prophets: how much more ought we little ones, to take heed that when we teache, we vtter not our own mindes, but the senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the holy ghost.</p>
               <p>The same vpon <hi>Mathew,</hi> in his 26. homily: no man ought (for the stablishing of doctrine) to vse any bookes, that be without the cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall scriptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ciprian</hi> in the exposition of the Creede, after that he hath rehearsed<note place="margin">All bookes vvhich be not in the Canon of the Bible, are called Apocripha, and are not sufficient to proue any arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of our faith.</note> the canonicall bookes of the Bible, he sayth. These be they, whiche our fathers haue included within the Canon, out of the which our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers would the doctrine of our faith to bee certaine: neuerthelesse there be other bookes which of our Elders were not called canonical but ecclesiasticall: as the booke of wisdome, the bokes of <hi>Sirach, To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie, Iudith, Machabees,</hi> and other. All which bookes, they would haue to be read in the church, but not aleaged as of authoritie to confirme any article of our faith. All other writinges they called Apocrypha, which they would in no wise to be red in the church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Athanasius</hi> against the Gentils. The holy Scriptures being inspired
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:176462:13"/> from God, are sufficient to all instruction of the truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Basilius</hi> in his booke of <hi>Ethickes,</hi> of his short definitions the. 26. Euery word and deede, that maketh for the certentie and suretie of good men, and the confusion of them that be euill, must be confirmed by the testimonie of Gods Scriptures. And those things, which either in our nature, or in the custome and maner of our life, are manifestlie knowne, must we vse, to confirme those thinges, which we doe and say.</p>
               <p>The same in his short definitions the first question. Whether it be lawfull or expedient for a man to permit himselfe to do what he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth good, without the testimony of the holy Scriptures. His answere. Seeing that our sauiour sayth of the holy Ghoste: he shall not speake of himselfe, but whatsoeuer hee hath heard, that shall hee speake: And of himselfe hee sayth the sonne can doe nothing of himselfe: And againe, I haue not spoken of my selfe, but he which sent me gaue me commaundement, what I should say, and what I should speake, and I know that his commaundement is eternall life: therefore those things, that I speak, I speak as the father said vnto me: who is he then, that will run into such madnesse, that he dare once thinke onely any thing of himselfe, seeing that he hath neede of the holy Ghost for his ayde, so that both in mynde, word and worke, he maye bee guided in the way of truth, and that he must needes walke in darkenesse, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he bee lightned with the sonne of righteousnesse, our Lord Iesus Christ, which shineth vpon vs with his commaundementes, as with bright beames? For the cōmaundemēt of the Lord is clere, and giueth light to the eyes. For of those thinges that are done, and commonly v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed among vs, some are by gods commaundement determined, and<note place="margin">No man can dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pense vvith gods lavve.</note> plainly set foorth in the holy Scriptures, and some not expressed. Of those that be expressed by the Scriptures, there is vtterly no power gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to any man (whatsoeuer he be in the whole world) eyther to doe<note place="margin">Thinges, that be not commaunded be indifferent to be vsed, or not v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed: but yet as charity requireth</note> any thing of those that be forbidden, or else to leaue vndon any thing of them that be commaunded: seeing that the Lord hath once com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded and said, whatsoeuer I commaund you, that take heede ye doe &amp;c. But of those thinges that are not expressed, the Apostle Paule hath giuen vs a rule, saying: I may doe all things but all things are not expedient. I may doe all thinges, but all thinges edyfie not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Isichius</hi> vpon <hi>Leuiticus. lib. 5. cap.</hi> 16. Let vs, which would haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny<note place="margin">Search no further then the Gospel</note> thing obserued of God, searche no more but that, which the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell doth giue vnto vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chrisostom</hi> vpon the. 24. <hi>cap.</hi> of <hi>Mathew. Homilia.</hi> 49. When you
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:176462:14"/> shall see the abhominable desolation stande in the holy place (that is) when you shall see vngodly heresie (whiche is the armie of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ)<note place="margin">In time of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, there is no meanes to try the truth and the true Church of Christ from Antichristes Church, but onlie by the Scriptures.</note> stande in the holy places of the churche: in that time let them, which are in Iurie, flie vnto the hilles (that is) let them that be in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendom resort vnto the scriptures. For like as the true Iewe is a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian (as the Apostle sayth, he is not a Iewe, which is outward, &amp;c.) in like maner the very Iurie is Christianitie, the Hilles are the Scriptures of the Apostles and Prophets. And why doth he commaund all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians at that time to resort to the Scriptures? for in this time since he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie hath preuailed in the church, there can be none other proofe of true christianitie, neither can there be any other refuge for Christen men, (willing to know the truth of the right faith) but onely vnto the holy scriptures. Before time, it was shewed by many other meanes, which was the true church of Christ, and which Gentilitie: but now there is no way to know it. And why? for all those things, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to Christ indeede, haue the heretickes in their Scisme: likewise churches, likewise the Scriptures of god, likewise Bishops, and other orders of clearkes, and likewise Baptisme, &amp; the Sacrament of thanks giuing, and (to conclude) Christ himselfe. Wherefore, hee that will know which is the true Church of Christ in this so great a confusiō of thinges being so like: how shall he knowe it but onely by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: It was also knowne, which was the true church of Christ, by their maners, when the conuersation of Christen men (either of all or many) was holy, which was not among the heathen.<note place="margin">An heauy saying, but alas to true.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But now christen men are become like, or worse then the gentiles or hereticks: yea and there is more continencie found amongst thē, then amongest Christians. Therefore he, that will know which is the true church of Christ, whereby shall he know it, but only by the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? the Lord therfore knowing that so great a confusion of things should come in the latter time, commaundeth that christen men, that be willing to know the right faith, should flie to none other thinges, but onely to the Scriptures. For if they loke vpon any other thing but only the Scriptures, they shall be offended and perish, not perceauing which is the true church: and so fall into the abhominable desolatiō, which standeth in the holy places of the church.</p>
               <p>The same in the vnperfect worke, <hi>Math.</hi> 7. Euery Preacher is a<note place="margin">Preachers must neither adde nor take ought from Godes vvord.</note> seruaunt of the law, which may neither add any thing aboue the law of his owne minde, nor withdraw any thing after his own vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: but preach that thing only, that is had in the lawe, as <hi>Salomon</hi> sayth, thou shalt adde nothing to the word of God, nor take oughte
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:176462:14"/> therefrom.</p>
               <p>The same of the holy ghost, <hi>tom.</hi> 3. If you see any man saying that<note place="margin">They that boaste themselues of the holy ghost vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Scripture, be void of the holy Ghost.</note> I haue the holy Ghost, and not speaking the Gospel, but his own: that man speaketh of himselfe, and the holy ghost is not in him. And after. If any of them therefore, which sayth he hath the holy ghost, &amp; spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth any thing of himselfe, and not forth of the Gospell, say: followe my councell, beleeue him not.</p>
               <p>The same in the 7. of <hi>Math. hom.</hi> 19. Vppon this texte: by their fruites ye shall know them. The fruites of man is the confession of his fayth, and the workes of his conuersation. If thou, therefore, shalt see a christen man, forthwith consider, if his confessiō agree with the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, he is a true Christian: but if not, he is (as Christ sayd) false. For so <hi>Iohn,</hi> when he wrote his Epistle of the heretickes, sayd not: if any come vnto you, not hauing the name of Christe, bidde him not God speede: but if any bring not this doctrine.</p>
               <p>The same in the same place, the 22. chapt. and 42. Homilie. Let vs<note place="margin">Heretickes ought first to be conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and after by reason.</note> first alleage the authoritie of the scriptures to the false forgers, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward let vs shew them reasons: and to them, that aske for any maner of purpose, first let vs declare vnto them the reason, and afterward the authoritie▪ that we may pacifie them with reason, and stablishe them with authoritie. For we ought to confute false interpreters, &amp; instruct them that search.</p>
               <p>The same vpon the last of the Romanes, vpon this texte. I beseech<note place="margin">To preach any thing besides gods vvord, is to sovve sedition &amp; heresie.</note> you brethren. He sayth that dissentions and slaunders, that is to saye, heresies, are brought in of those, which bring any thing besides the doctrine and learning of the Apostles.</p>
               <p>The same vpon the latter Epistle to Timothie, the third chapter.<note place="margin">All thinges may be determined by the Scriptures.</note> There is nothing that cannot be determined by the Scriptures, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue, if it be to be reprooued (that is to say) lyes: to correcte, and to teache in righteousnesse. If it be needefull (sayth hee) that any thing should be corrected or instructed, that is to be made continent and sober vnto righteousnesse, and to execute those thinges that bee iust: all that shall be giuen by the Scripture, that the man of God may bee perfect: the amendment (sayth he) is prepared by the scriptures, that nothing may be lacking to that man, that walketh after God.</p>
               <p>The same vpon <hi>Math. 22. cap. hom.</hi> 4. Whatsoeuer is requisite for<note place="margin">The holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture conteineth al thinges needefull for our saluation.</note> our saluation, is alreadie contayned in the holy scriptures. He that is ignorant, shall finde there what he may learne. He that is stubborne, and a sinner, may finde there scourges of the iudgementes to come, the which he may feare: he, that is troubled, may find there the ioyes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:176462:15"/> and promises of euerlasting life, through the beholding of the which he may be stirred to good workes.</p>
               <p>The same vpon the 2. of the <hi>Thessalo. cap.</hi> 2. All thinges be playne and cleare in the scriptures, and what thinges soeuer be needefull, be manifest there.</p>
               <p>The same vpon the 2. to <hi>Timo. cap.</hi> 3. If there be any thing neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be known, or not to be knowne, we shall learne it by the holye scriptures: if we shall neede to reprooue a falshod, wee shall fetche it from thence: if to be corrected, to be chastened, to be exhorted, or cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, to be short, if ought lack that ought to be taught or learned, we shall also learne it out of the scriptures.<note place="margin">A preacher must speake nothing but out of Gods mouth.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The same, Hom. 1. <hi>Titum.</hi> Like as the beadle crieth openly to all thē that be in the Court, so do we preach opēly: but on that conditiō, that we ad nothing, but preach only that thing, that we haue hearde. For the office of a criar is to speake out those things that be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, and not to adde, chaunge, or take away any thing.</p>
               <p>The same vpon the later Epistle to <hi>Timoth. cap.</hi> 3. Therefore, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">Beleeue him not, that speaketh vvithout the scripture. He, that beleueth the Gospell vvritten, needeth beleeue no more.</note> oughte they to bee beleeued at all, excepte they speake those thinges which be agreeable to the scriptures.</p>
               <p>The same vpon the 20 chap. of <hi>John Hom.</hi> 89. But why did not the Apostles write all things? Cheefly because of the multitude of them. Moreouer they did consider, that he, which would not beleeue these, would not beleeue more: but he that beleeueth these, neede no more to attaine faith.</p>
               <p>The same vpon <hi>Genesis</hi> the 12. Homilie. The holy scripture expoū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it selfe, and suffereth not the hearer to erre.</p>
               <p>The same in the same booke, <hi>Hom.</hi> 21. Neither hath the scripture<note place="margin">Not mans vvise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome but the holy ghost is the true expositor of the scripture.</note> of God any neede of mans wisedome that it may be vnderstand, but the reuelacion of the holy Ghost: that, the true meaning being suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thereout, great aduauntage may grow to vs thereby.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hieronymus</hi> in the Prologue of the Bible to <hi>Pauline.</hi> After he had<note place="margin">Nothing is of like authoritie vvith the holy scripture.</note> recited the bookes of the new testament and the olde, he sayth: I pray thee deare brother, among these liue, muse vpō these, know nothing else, seeke for none other thing.</p>
               <p>Againe vppon the bookes of the olde and newe testament: These writings be holy, these bokes be sound both in nūber and authoritie, there is none other to bee compared to these, whatsoeuer is besides these, may in no wise be receiued among these holy thinges.<note place="margin">Gods vvord cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of all traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Apostolik as they call them, vvhich be be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>side the same vvord, vve ought not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv any mans doctrine vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Gods vvo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d. the Apostles grounded al their doctrine vpon the Lavve and Prophetes. To build vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doctorssaying vvithout Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or reason a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, vvere to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv pithagoras, rather then Christ.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Againe vpon the first chapt. of <hi>Agge.</hi> All other things which they seeke out, and inuēt at their own pleasure without the auctoritie and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:176462:15"/> testimonie of the scriptures (as though they were the traditions of the Apostles) the sword of God cutteth off.</p>
               <p>Againe in his little Commentaries to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> vppon this place: condescend to no man, this perswasion is not of God, whiche hath called you: thus he interpreteth it: ye ought neither to consent to them, nor to me, without the word of God.</p>
               <p>Againe vpon <hi>Math. cap.</hi> 13. vpon this place: euery learned scribe. Whatsoeuer the Apostles preached, they confirmed it by the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the law and Prophets.</p>
               <p>The same to <hi>Minerius</hi> &amp; <hi>Alexander.</hi> Not according to <hi>Pithagoras</hi> disciples, the opiniō, geuen sentence vpō afore hand by the doctours, but the reason of the doctrine is to be wayed: but if any man, that is of a contrary sect, do murmure why I read their expositiōs, vnto whose doctrines I do not cōsent: let him know, that I willingly heare this of the Apostle: prooue all things, but cleaue to that which is good, and the wordes of our sauiour, saying: be ye tried bankers, and if any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney be counterfeited, and haue not the Emperours stamp, nor be cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant money, refuse it, but that, that sheweth the face of Christe in the cleare light, bestow it in the purse of your hart.</p>
               <p>The same vpon <hi>Mat. cap.</hi> 23. That which hath no auctoritie of the scriptures, may as easily be reiected, as prooued.</p>
               <p>The same in the 98. Psal. All that euer we speake, wee oughte to prooue it by the scriptures.</p>
               <p>The same in the 86. Psalme. The Lord shall speake in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the people, &amp;c. and how shall he speake, not with words, but with scriptures of those Princes that were in it, that is, of the Apostles and Euangelists. And mark what he saith: of those Princes that were in it, and not which are. So that (the Apostles except) whatsoeuer shal be spoken afterwarde, let it be cut of, and haue none auctoritie. Bee a man therefore neuer so holy, be he neuer so well learned, after the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles he hath none auctoritie: for the Lorde speaketh in the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of those princes, that were in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ambrosius</hi> of virgines <hi>lib. 3. cap.</hi> 1. We iustly do condemn all new<note place="margin">To teach that as needefull to sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation vvhich Christ hath not taught, is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</note> thinges, which Christ hath not taught: for Christe is the waye to the faithfull. If therefore we our selues preach any thing, that Christ hath not taught, iudge that abhominable.</p>
               <p>The same in the Psalme 118. The word of God is the liuely meat of our soules, with the which it is nourished, fead and gouerned: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">The soule liueth onely by the vvord of God.</note> is there any thing else, that maketh a reasonable soule to liue, but the word of God.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:176462:16"/> The same in his booke of Paradise, Chap. 12. By that which <hi>Eua</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded<note place="margin">Nothing is to be added to the vvord of God, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be for a good purpose.</note> to the word of God, yea though it be for a good purpose. For if thou put too, or take away any thing, it appeareth to be a transgressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the commaundement: for there oughte no thing to be added, although it seeme good.</p>
               <p>The same in the Epistle to the Galathians, Chap. 1. Neyther (saith<note place="margin">As vvell, vvho preacheth beside the Gospell as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cursed.</note> the Apostle) if they preache contrary: but if they preache any thing besides that that we haue preached, that is, if they adde any thing to it at all, holde them accursed. Neither doe I except my selfe, If I put too any thing beside that which was preached afore.</p>
               <p>The same, in the same place. He doth affirme the Gospell, whiche<note place="margin">Euen the Apostles preching besides the gospell are not to be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</note> he had preached vnto them, to be so firme and true: that although it should chaunce themselues (that is to say, the Apostles) being chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, to preach any other thing, he teacheth that they ought not to be heard.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Augustine</hi> of the consent of the Euangelistes. Hee that sente the<note place="margin">Christ made all to be vvritten, that he vvould vve should read.</note> Prophets before his incarnation, the same sent also his Apostles after his ascension, yea and by that manhood which he tooke vpon him, he is the head of all his disciples, whiche are members of his bodye: therefore forasmuch as they wrot those things which he shewed and taught them, it ought not to be sayd that he wrot them not, seing that his mēbers wrot that, which they knew by their head teaching them.<note place="margin">VVe are as vvell bound to beleeue that, vvhich the Apostles vvrote: as though Christ had vvritten it vvith his ovvne hand.</note> For whatsoeuer he would haue vs to read, both of his deeds &amp; words, that commaunded he them to write, as his handes of his body. Who so euer doth perceaue this fellowship of vnitie &amp; agreement of mē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, ministring vnder one head in diuerse offices: hee shall none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwayes take that, that he readeth in the gospell (the disciples de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring it) then if he had seene the very hand of the Lord, whiche hee bare in his owne body, writing it.</p>
               <p>The same to <hi>Ʋincent.</hi> against the Donatists, the 6. tom. pa. 116. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist.<note place="margin">The Church is knovvne by the scripture.</note> 48. We therefore for this cause are certain and sure, that no man ought to withdraw himselfe from the communion of all men. And let none of vs seeke the church in our own righteousnesse, but in the holy scripture.</p>
               <p>The same to the <hi>Mandarens</hi> Epi. 42. Al that euer our Elders made<note place="margin">All that concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth true religion is contained in the scripture.</note> mention of to be done towards mankind in times past, and deliuered to vs: all things also which we see, &amp; deliuer to our posteritie, which doe appertaine to getting and maintaining of true religion, the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God did not passe with silence.</p>
               <p>Againe to the brethren in the wildernesse. Reade the holye Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:176462:16"/> wherein ye shall finde fully what is to be followed, and what to be auoided.</p>
               <p>The same of nature and grace. <hi>lib. 1. cap.</hi> 61. Iowe my consent to the canonicall Scriptures only, without any refusall.</p>
               <p>The same vpon <hi>John.</hi> 49. treatise, <hi>cap.</hi> 11. Not all thinges that the Lord Iesus did, are written, as the same Euangelist witnesseth: for the Lord both did and said many things, that are not written: but things were chosen out to be written, which seemed sufficient for the salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the beleeuers.</p>
               <p>The same against <hi>Faustus lib. 23. cap.</hi> 9. That which <hi>Faustus</hi> put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth<note place="margin">No man is bound to beleeue farther then the holye scriptures teache</note> foorth vpon the byrth of <hi>Mary,</hi> that she had a certaine Priest to her father, of the tribe of <hi>Leuy</hi> named <hi>Joachim:</hi> because it is not cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall it doth not binde me.</p>
               <p>The same of Baptisme against the <hi>Donatistes lib. 2. cap.</hi> 6. Lette vs<note place="margin">The balance to trie the truth is the holy scripture</note> not bring deceatfull balances, wherein we may weigh what we will after our owne pleasure, saying this is heauie, this is light: but let vs bring the diuine balances of the holy Scriptures, as of the treasures of the Lord, &amp; in it let vs weigh what is heauy, yea let vs not weigh, but rather acknowledge the thinges, that are weighed of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Againe vpon <hi>John</hi> the 46. treatise. Sitting vpon the chaire of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">They that sit on Moses chaire and teach their ovvne doctrine, are not to be beleeued.</note> they teach the law of God: therefore God teacheth by them. But if they will teach their own, heare them not, doe not after them: for truely such men search their owne, but not those things, which are of Iesus Christ.</p>
               <p>Againe <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. of the christen doctrine, <hi>cap. vlt.</hi> Howe muche lesse<note place="margin">All euill is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the scripture, and all good thinges are there found.</note> the aboundance of golde, siluer and clothing, whiche that people brought with them foorth of <hi>Aegipt,</hi> is in comparison of the riches which afterward they had at <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> whiche aboue all other was shewed in King <hi>Salomon:</hi> so let all knowledge (whiche is in deede profitably gathered out of the bookes of the Gentils) be such, if it bee compared to the knowledge of gods scriptures. For whatsoeuer man learneth without them, if it be euill, there it is condemned: if it bee profitable, there it is found. And seing then euery man shall finde all thinges there, which he hath profitably learned other where: muche more aboundantly shall he finde those thinges there, whiche can no where at all else be learned, but onely in the maruailous deepenesse, and wonderfull humilitie of those scriptures.</p>
               <p>The same in his booke of nature and grace, the 16. chapt. We may<note place="margin">VVe may lavvful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dissent from al doctrine, excepte the Scriptures only.</note> lawefully sometime dissent from other learning, but to the Catholick learning euery man must giue place, euery man must subscribe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:176462:17"/> he be lay man, Priest, King, or Emperour.</p>
               <p>The same in his 2. booke of the Christian doctrine. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. After that he hath numbred the canonicall bookes, he sayth thus. In all these bokes they that feare God &amp; are tamed through godlines do searche the will of God. The firste note of which labour and trauaile (as wee sayde) is to know these bookes, and if as yet wee cannot vnderstande them, yet let vs by reading get them in memorie, or not to be altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorant in them. Furthermore those thinges which be plainely<note place="margin">All thinges that concerne faith, hope loue, and go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d maners: are conteined in the Scripture.</note> contained therein, whether they be preceptes of liuing, or else of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing, are earnestly and diligently to be searched: which, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the more euery man findeth, so much the more is he apt in his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding. In these therefore, which are euidently contained in the scripture, are found al things, which containe fayth, maners of liuing, hope and loue.</p>
               <p>The same of the vnitie of the Church, <hi>cap.</hi> 3. Let vs not heare, I say:<note place="margin">Not vvhat vve say, but vvhat the lord, that must be heard. The church is knovvne by the Scriptures.</note> thou sayst, but let vs heare: thus sayth the Lorde. There are, out of doubt, the Lordes bookes, to the auctoritie whereof we both consēt, we both beleeue, we both serue. Let vs searche the church there, let vs discusse our cause there.</p>
               <p>Againe in his second booke of Baptisme, against the Donatistes, <hi>cap.</hi> 3. Who is hee, that knoweth not, that the scripture canonicall is so contayned within his certayne boundes of the newe and olde Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stamente, and is so to bee preferred aboue all other writings of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, that a man may not at all either doubte or dispute of it, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">VVe may doubt of all mens doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine but not of holy Scriptvres. If gods scripturs cannot discusse a matter in doubt let man neuer go about to discusse it.</note> any thing be true or right, that he is sure is written in it: but the letters of all other Bishops, which are, or shalbe hereafter written be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the Canonicall scriptures, alreadie confirmed, may bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued, either by more graue aucthoritie of other Bishoppes or learned men, and by the wordes of euery man, that is better seene in the matter.</p>
               <p>Again in his second boke of the merites and forgiuenesse of sinnes <hi>cap. vlt. tom.</hi> 7. Where disputation is had of a doubtfull matter, if the certayne and cleare doctrine of the Scriptures of God do not help it: mans reason ought to stay it self, nothing leaning to either part. For though I know not how to expresse euery one of these thinges: yet I beleeue surely, that the scriptures of God should be most plain here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, if a man might not be ignoraunt hereof withoute the losse of that saluation that is promised him.</p>
               <p>Againe in his booke of pastors. He appointed the hilles of Israell<note place="margin">VVho feedeth vvith the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures, feedeth safely▪ Other therefore vvith vnvvritten veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties feede vntru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.</note> the authoures of the scriptures of God, feede there that you maye
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:176462:17"/> feede safely. Whatsoeuer you heare out of that let it sauoure well to you, whatsoeuer is beesides that, refuse it, least you wander in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to cloudes.</p>
               <p>Get you to the hille of the Scriptures, there be the pleasures of your hartes, there is no noysom, hurtfull or venemous thinges, no inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient thinges, there be most plentifull pastures.</p>
               <p>Againe of Christian doctrine <hi>lib. 2. cap.</hi> 9. In these thinges that bee<note place="margin">In the Scripture are all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary for faith and goodlife, vvhich tvvo suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fise for saluation.</note> plainly set fourth in the Scriptures, are found all thinges, that containe faith and maners of lyuing, that is to wit, hope and charetye. Then after a certaine familiaritie had with the speeche of the Scripture of God, we must goe to expound, and discus those things that be darke, that (to giue light to dark speaches) examples may be taken out of the more plain places, and some testimonies of places, being certain, may take away the doubt of the vncertain sentences.</p>
               <p>Againe of the Christian doctrine the. 3. <hi>lib. cap.</hi> 26. Darke places are to be expounded by plainer places. That is the sured way, to expound one Scripture by another.</p>
               <p>Againe to <hi>Vincent</hi> the <hi>Donatist Epistola.</hi> 48. This kind of learning (speaking of the olde writers doinges is not to be read with necessitie of beleefe, but with libertie of iudgement. And after. There (that is) in the holy Scriptures, it is not lawfull to say, the authour of this booke perceaued not the truth: but eyther that the booke is false, or the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter<note place="margin">If any mans say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or vvriting cannot be proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by plain Scripture or good reason, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered of the same a man may alovve or refuse it, as him liketh.</note> hath erred, or thou vnderstandest it not. But in the workes of al them that come after, (which be conteined in innumerable bookes, yet in no wise to be compared to the most holy excellencie of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall Scriptures) although in som of them be found the same truth, yet the authoritie is far vnlike.</p>
               <p>Therefore, if it fortune any thing in them to bee thought to dissent from the truth, because they are not so vnderstand as they be spoken: yet the reader or hearer, hath his free iudgement, so that eyther hee may alow that, that pleaseth him, or reiect that which offendeth him. And therefore all such like (except they maye bee defended either by good reason or by the Canonicall aucthoritie, that it may be prooued that they are so indeede, or may bee so, because either it is there dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, or declared) if it displease any man, or if he will not beleue it, he is not to be blamed therefore.</p>
               <p>The same in the same place Epistola. 48. Gather not (my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) agaynst so manye, so cleare, and so vndoubted witnesses of the Scriptures, sentences misunderstanded, oute of the writinges of Bishopes, either of ours, of Hillarie, or <hi>Ciprian</hi> Bishop and martir
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:176462:18"/> of the Church: for we must put a diuersity betwixt this kinde of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting<note place="margin">The olde vvrite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s are not of suche authority, but that vve may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie them, if they dissent from the holy Scriptures.</note> and the Canonicall Scriptures. For these are not so to be red, as though a witnes might be aleaged out of them, so that no man might think otherwise, if they fortune to Iudge otherwise, then the truth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth.</p>
               <p>The same to <hi>Ierome.</hi> I haue learned to giue this reuerence and honour to those onely writers, which be now called Canonicall, that I dare be bold to beleeue that none of them did erre any thing at al in writing. But if I find any thing in those Scriptures, that seemeth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the truth: I doubt not, but that either the booke is false, or the interpreter did not attain the thing that was spoken, or else I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand it not.</p>
               <p>But al other authors, (be they neuer so excellent both in vertue and<note place="margin">VVe may not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nk al, that the old fathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s did vvrite, to be true.</note> learning) I doe so reade them, not that I think it true that they writ, because they thought so: but because they could perswade me either by other Canonicall Scriptures, or by some probable reasons, a thing not altogether abhorring from the truth.</p>
               <p>The same against <hi>Cresconium</hi> a Gramarian <hi>Lib. 2. Capit.</hi> 32. I am<note place="margin">All mens vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings ought to be vveighed by the Canonicall scriptures.</note> not bound to his authority. For I doe not accoumpt <hi>Ciprians</hi> writings as Canonical, but weigh them by the Canonical Scriptures: and that in them, which agreeth with the Canonicall Scriptures, I alow to his praise, but that, that agreeth not, by his fauour I refuse.</p>
               <p>The same to <hi>Vincent Victor.</hi> I cannot, nor ought not to denie, that<note place="margin">He confesseth many errours in his ovvn bookes and others also.</note> lyke as in mine elders, so also in my so many bookes, be many things: that by iust iudgement, (without rashenesse) maye be reproued.</p>
               <p>The same in the Prologue of his booke of the Trinity. Be not boūd<note place="margin">Beleeue not his vvritinges except thou be suer of them by the Scriptures.</note> to my writinges, as to the Canonicall Scriptures: But if thou find any thing in them, which thou diddest not beleeue, strayghtway beleeue it: in these that thou art not sure of, except thou certainly vnderstand it, beleeue it not certainly.</p>
               <p>The same to <hi>Fortunate Epistola.</hi> 198. Neither ought wee to alowe<note place="margin">VVe ought not to esteme mans vvri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinges further, then they agree vvith the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: but may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse them at our pleasures.</note> the reasoninges of any men, whatsoeuer they be, (although they bee Catholike and lawdable men) as the Canonicall Scriptures, so that it shal not be lawful for vs (sauing the reuerence that is due to those mē) to reprooue, and refuse any thing in their writinges, if it chaunce that they haue iudged otherwise then truth is: the same truth, by Gods helpe, beeing vnderstand either of other men, or of vs. For I am euen suche a one in other mens writinges, as I would men should bee in myne.</p>
               <p>The same in the same place. Let vs seeke no further, then is written
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:176462:18"/> of god our sauiour, least a man would know more, then the Scriptures witnesse.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cirill lib.</hi> 6. Vpon <hi>Leuiticus.</hi> There be two offices of a Bishop, to<note place="margin">Vnderstand the vvord vvritten, for they that learne of it, learne of God.</note> learne the Scriptures of God, and by oft reading to digest the same, or else to teach the people: but let him teach those things which he hath learned of God, and not of his owne hart or by mans vnderstanding, but those thinges which the holy ghost teacheth.</p>
               <p>The same in <hi>John, cap.</hi> 6. He saith, by this we learne, that onely<note place="margin">All thinges per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining to doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and good maners, are in the vvord vvritten, vvhich is suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</note> Christ ought to be folowed as a master, and we must cleaue vnto him onely.</p>
               <p>The same in <hi>Iohn. cap.</hi> 20. Not all thinges, that the Lord did, are written: but those thinges that the writers thought sufficient, as wel to good maners as to doctrine, that wee, shining with a constaunt fayth, good workes and vertues, maye come to the Kingdome of heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fulgence</hi> in his Sermon of the confessors. In the worde of God is<note place="margin">Note this holy fathers vvordes, and print them in your hartes for euer.</note> plentie for the strong man to eate, there is inoughe for the chyld to sucke, there is also mylke to drinke, wherewith the tender infancye of the faithfull may bee nourished, and strong meate, wherewith the lustie youth of thē, that be perfect, may receaue the spiritual encrease<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of holy vertue There, prouision is made for the saluation of all men, whom the lord doth vouchsafe to saue: there is that that is agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to all ages: there is also that, which is mete for al states. There we learn the commaundements, which we ought to do: there we know the rewardes, which we hope for.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregory</hi> in <hi>Iob. lib. 16. Cap.</hi> 28. He that prepareth himselfe to the<note place="margin">If preachers ought so, then so ought all others: for they all are prepared to come to one end by one ordinary rule.</note> office of a true preacher, muste needes fetche the foundation of his matters out of the holy Scriptures. So that all that he sayth, he must reduce it to the first beginning of Gods aucthoritie, and in that stay the effecte of his sayinges. For as I haue sayde manye tymes afore: Heretickes when they studye to mayntayne theire froward doctrine surely they bring foorth those thinges, that are not contained in the holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theophilactus</hi> vppon this place of Paule, the laste to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines:</hi> I beseeche you brethren, marke them whiche cause diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and geue occasion of euill, contrary to the doctrine which you haue learned, and auoid thē: for they that are such serue not the Lord Iesus Christ, but their own bellies, and with sweet preachings &amp; flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering words deceaue the harts of the innocents: Here saith <hi>Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lactus</hi> that they bring in diuisions and occasions of euill, which bring
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:176462:19"/> foorth any thing beside the doctrine and learning of the Apostles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Damascenus lib. 1. cap.</hi> 1. Al that euer was deliuered by the law, the Prophets, the Apostles &amp; the Euangelists, we receiue, acknowledge, and giue reuerence vnto them, searching nothing besides them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bruno</hi> in the second to <hi>Timothie.</hi> Doubtlesse the holye Scriptures are able to instruct thee to saluation. For euery scripture being inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from God, that is to say, spiritually vnderstande after the will of God, is profitable to teache them that be ignoraunt, to reprooue (that<note place="margin">The scriptures on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly are sufficient for matters of saluation.</note> is) to conuince them that speake against the fayth, to correct sinners, such as denie not themselues to be sinners: to instruct those that bee yet rude and simple, to instruct (I say) in righteousnesse, that they may be made righteous by putting away their former instructions of infidelitie (I say) that he may be so taughte, that, as muche as in the teacher lieth, he that is taughte, may be the perfite man of God: so perfite, that he may be instruct to doe euery good worke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beda</hi> in the 1. Epist. of <hi>Peter, cap.</hi> 5. If any man speake, let him speak as the wordes of God, fearing least he saye or commaunde any thing besides the wil of God, or besides that, which is manifestly commaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the holy scriptures, and be found as a false witnesse of God, or<note place="margin">If any man speak, let him speake according to the vvord of God: except he vvill be called by these names here expressed.</note> a committer of sacrilege, or a bringer in of any straunge thing frō the Lordes doctrine, or else leaue out or passe ouer any thing that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth God, seeing that Christ most plainely commaundeth the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the truth, concerning them whome they had taught, saying: teache them to keepe all thinges, that I haue commaunded you. Yea euen the same, which he had commaunded and none other, and hee commaunded his preachers to commaūd their hearers to keepe, not some of these, but all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anselmus</hi> Bishop in his booke of Virginitie, <hi>cap.</hi> 24. Gods lawe forbiddeth to follow the steppes of the Catholick or vniuersall fayth any more, then the iudgement of the Canonicall truth commaūdeth<note place="margin">VVe may not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the generall fayth, except the same agree vvith Gods vvord.</note> to beleeue. And all other Apocriphall lies, the good policies of the best learned fathers haue stablished in their decrees, vtterly to reiecte and to banish them cleane, as horrible thondringes of wordes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lyrane</hi> vpon the last chapter of the Prouerbes. Like as in a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes shippe are caried diuerse thinges necessarie for mans life: so in the Scripture are contained all thinges needefull to saluation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas of Aquine.</hi> The holye Scripture is the rule of our fayth, wherevnto it is neither lawfull to adde, nor take any thing away. But the truth of our fayth is contayned in the holy scriptures diffusely and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:176462:19"/> diuerse wayes, in some places darkely, and to trie out the truth of our<note place="margin">The truth of our<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> faith is contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the vvord vvritten.</note> fayth by the scriptures, is required long studie and excercise: to the which all they cannot come, that need to know the truth of the faith, the more part whereof being occupied with other businesse, cannot attende to studie. And therefore it was needefull out of the sentences of holy scripture to gather something into a short sum, which should be set foorth for all men to beleeue, whiche is not added to the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but rather taken out of the scriptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scotus</hi> in the Prologue of sentences quest. 2. Question. Whether knowledge aboue nature, sufficient for a man in this life, be sufficiētly set foorth in the holy scripture. The Question is not whether any things be true that are not written, or whether God, since the creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and redemption of the world, hath done or sayd any thing, that is not written, and receaued of the Churche for the holye scripture: but this is the question, whether the worde of God written be sufficient for our saluation: or whether a Christen man be bound to beleeue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, that cannot be proued by the holy Scripture. And this graū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that all thinges that may be gathered out of the Scripture, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thing that vpon any truth graunted may be prooued by a good argument of the scripture, doth pertaine to the holye scripture: this graunted I say, he concludeth that all thinges, necessarie for our sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, are fully conteined in the holy scripture.</p>
               <p>¶ The schoole authors call the stay of our fayth, the truth shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God, and contayned in the Canon of the Bible.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:176462:20"/>
               <head>That the general Councels without the worde of God, are not sufficient to make Articles of our fayth. CAP. III.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ʋsebius</hi> in his ecclesiasticall historie, <hi>lib.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">They vvere ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in the spirite of pride and enuy, and not in the spirite of meekenesse and loue.</note>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 8. The head rulers of the Churche, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting Gods commaundements were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed one agaynste another with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, zeale, enuye, pryde, malice, and hatred, so that they thoughte rather that they occupied the roome of Tirantes then of Priestes. And also, forgetting Christian humilitie and sinceritie, they did celebrate the holy mysteries with vnholy handes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorie Nazianzen</hi> to <hi>Procopius.</hi> Vndoubtedly I thinke thus, if I<note place="margin">Note these vvordes diligent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, and forget them not.</note> must needes write the truth, that al assemblies of Bishops are to be es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chued. For I neuer saw good ende of any synode, that did not rather bring in euils, then put them away: for the lustes of strife and desire, and of Lordship raigne there.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Augustine</hi> in his seconde booke and thirde chapter againste the<note place="margin">Counsails are not of such au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, that vvhatsoeuer they decree, must be holden for truth.</note> Donatists. The Councels, whiche are kepte through euery region or prouince, without all cloakings, oughte to giue place to the generall councels, which are made of all Christendome: yea and the former generall Counsels, oughte ofte times to bee reformed by the latter councelles, if anye thing in them doe chaunce to erre from the truth.</p>
               <p>Augustine against <hi>Maximinum</hi> the Bishop of the Arrianes. lib. 3 Ca. 4. But now neither ought I to aleage the counsel of <hi>Nice,</hi> nor thou<note place="margin">The scripture must trie all.</note> the counsel of <hi>Arimine,</hi> to take aduauntage thereby: for neither am I bound nor held by the authoritie of this, nor thou of that. Let matter with matter, cause with cause, or reason with reason, trye the matter by the aucthoritie of Scriptures, not proper witnesses to any of vs, but indifferent witnesses for vs both.</p>
               <p>Gerson. Wee ought rather beleeue the saying of any teacher,<note place="margin">Mark this.</note> armed with the Canonycall Scripture, then the Popes determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:176462:20"/>
               <p>The same. More credite is to be giuen to a man, that is singularlye<note place="margin">Reade ye Papists, and be no longer ignorant.</note> learned in the Scripture, bringing foorth catholick authoritie, then to the generall councell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Panormitan</hi> in <hi>cap. significasti.</hi> A simple lay man, bringing foorth<note place="margin">Counsels maye and doe erre oft times.</note> the scriptures, is to be beleeued rather then an whole Counsell. For a counsell may erre, as it hath afore times erred, as did the counsell of <hi>Melchildense</hi> and <hi>Aquisgranum,</hi> of contracting of Matrimonie. The Councell of <hi>Constance</hi> among other Articles of <hi>Iohn Hus</hi> and <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> of <hi>Prage,</hi> vniustly condemned, condemned also this Article for heresie: that the two natures (that is) the diuine and humanitie be one Christ, which is a necessarie article of our faith, expressed in the Creed of <hi>Athanasius</hi> called <hi>Qui cunque vult,</hi> where it is reade: The righte Fayth is, that we beleeue and confesse, that our Lord Iesus Christe the<note place="margin">Reade the Psalm.</note> sonne of God is God and man, and a little after: Like as the reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble soule and the flesh is one man, so God and man is one Christ: the same is also decreede by the counsell of <hi>Nice</hi> and diuers other catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like counsels, and it is the doctrine of the Church at this time. Finallye it may be prooued by the expresse word of God, and yet these malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Cleargie were not ashamed to condemn the same for an heresie.</p>
               <p>¶ Note here gentle Reader, vnto what shamelesse and detestable he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies their popish, yea Antichristian generall counsels haue fallen, of the which they boast so much, that they cannot erre, and wherevpon chiefly they build all their errours and heresies. Moreouer the moste part of the good lawes and Canons be in maner altogither abrogated and no where kept: part whereof I shall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse.</p>
               <div type="canons">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:176462:21"/>
                  <head>Canons of the Apostles and Counsels not kept nor vsed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et not a Bishop, Priest or Deacon, by any meanes<note place="margin">Canon 3.</note> put awaye his owne wyfe vnder pretence of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but if he doe, let him bee excommunicated: and if he so continue let him be deposed.</p>
                  <p>Canon. 4. Let no Bishoppe, Priestor Deacon bee receaued into an other Bishops Diocese, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a testimoniall of his good behauiour: and when they haue deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered their writings, let them be diligently examined if they be god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Preachers.</p>
                  <p>¶ If these 2 lawes were throughly executed by indifferent Iudges being no Priests, the realm of <hi>England</hi> should not swarm so full of rū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agates, adulterous, &amp; sodomicall Priestes. For in <hi>Wales</hi> for their cradle crownes payd to the Ordinarie, they kept their concubines or harlots openly: &amp; in <hi>England</hi> many great beneficed men keepe their harlots at rack and maunger without any punishment, excepte it be by bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing of the ordinaries priuily: and all shame set aside, they haue their own knowne bastardes wayting vppon them in sighte of the whole world. But the poore purgatorie Priests whē they be taken in opē ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulterie, flee from east to west, from north to south, frō Diocese to Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cese, &amp; there be receaued without any letters testimonial at al: where they be taken for honest &amp; chast Priests. But if the rich Priests were de priued of al their promotiōs, so oft as they be known to be fornicators (as they ought to be) &amp; the pore Priests not receaued into any strange diocese, without testimonie of his honest demeanour, from his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ordinarie: you should scarcely finde Priestes: for euery third be benefice of <hi>England,</hi> &amp; the Priests thēselues would be the first earnest suters that they might haue their lawfull wiues of their owne: but as long as they be their own iudges (according to the old prouerbe, one skabbed horse gnappeth another) what for fauor &amp; friendship what for money &amp; for slaūdering of their order: they winke one at anothers faults, &amp; help to cloke the same insomuch, that within my memorie, which is aboue 30 yeares, &amp; also by enformation of other, that be 20. yeres elder thē I, I could neuer perceaue or learn, that any one Priest, vnder the Popes kingdome, was euer punished for aduoutrie by his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:176462:21"/> ordinarie. And yet not long ago, a Petycanon of a Cathedrall Church<note place="margin">O vvhat a coure is this, that in suspicion of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie acquiteth no man, and in cause of adultery con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth no priest, be his crime neuer so o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly knovvne.</note> in <hi>England</hi> was accused of buggerie, by three boyes of the gramer schole, to the vicedeane or subdeane of the same Church, a man not vnlike to a monke called <hi>Iodocus:</hi> of whome <hi>Erasmus</hi> maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he were worthy to walke openly with a bell and a cockes combe, if he were not set forth vnder the holy habet of a monke. But when he perceaued, that the saide Priest could not purge himselfe of the foresaide crime, he priuely payed him his quarters wages before hand, and suffered him to depart withoute farther tryall of the sayde crime: and now he ietteth in london, with side gowne and sarcenet tippet, as good a virgin prieste as the beste. If I should but breefely touch all the Histories, that I haue knowen of the incontinencye of Priests, it would growe to a worke thrise greater, then all my whole booke, and it would mak some of the proudest of them to blushe, if they be not past all shame: but I will not blot my good paper with so euill matter: although they bee not ashamed openly to blotte and stain their own names with crymes, worthy of such reproch and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy.</p>
                  <p>Let not any Bishop, Priest or Deacon, in any wise take vpon him<note place="margin">Cano. 7.</note> any secular businesse: but if he doe, let him be excommunicated.</p>
                  <p>¶ But now such shamelesse contemners they be of their own lawes, which they so greatly extoll and bind all other to keepe: that they be hunters, faukoners, stewardes, surueyars and receiuers to al great men, yea and to the Bishopes themselues.</p>
                  <p>If any Priest or Deacon, or any other of the number of Priesthood,<note place="margin">Cano. 9.</note> do not receaue at the communion let him shew his cause: if it be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable, let him bee pardoned: if not, let him be depriued from the Communion.</p>
                  <p>It is meete to put of from the communion al Christen men (which<note place="margin">Cano. 10.</note> enter into the Church, and heare the Scriptures, but continue not in prayer vntil masse be done: nor receaue there the holy communion:) as disturbers, of the quietnesse of the Church.</p>
                  <p>¶ By these two Canons be subuerted, and vtterly ouerthrowne, all priuate masses, where the Priest onely receiueth.</p>
                  <p>Let the olde custom continnue still in <hi>Egipt, Libia</hi> and <hi>Pentapoly,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The counsel of nice, cano. 6.</note> that the Byshop of <hi>Alexandrye</hi> haue power ouer all these: for as much as the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> hath a lyke custome. At <hi>Antioche</hi> also, and other prouinces: let their honour bee reserued to euery Church. Because there be some that kneele at their prayers on the Sonday and<note place="margin">The counsel of nice cano. 20.</note> in whitson weeke: be it therefore ordeined by this holy counsell, that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:176462:22"/> all men stande at their prayers, for so muche as it is a conuenient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome, fit to be kept in all Churches.</p>
                  <p>¶ But now Antichrist of Rome, contrarie to this decree, hath extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led himselfe aboue his fellow Bishops, as Gods Vicar, yea rather as God himselfe: and taketh vpon him authoritie ouer Kinges and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, and sitteth in the temple of God, that is, in the consciences of men, and causeth his decrees to be more regarded then Gods lawes, yea and for money he dispenseth with Gods lawes and all other, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing men licence to breake them.</p>
                  <p>If any Priest be found eating in a common Alehouse, let him be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated.<note place="margin">The Counsell of Nice. 6.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>If any man iudge that a maried Priest ought not to offer, as it were<note place="margin">The Counsell of Gansgrense.</note> for his mariage sake: and for that cause doe abstaine from his obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, let him be excommunicated.</p>
                  <p>¶ But now maried Priestes be excommunicated, and except they will forsake their lawfull wiues, they shall be burned therefore.</p>
                  <p>For as much as there are some, which pray standing, both on the<note place="margin">Ibidem. 7.</note> Sonday and in Whitson weeke: it is therefore ordayned by this holy counsel, that because it is a cōuenient custome, &amp; agreeable through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all churches, that mē should make their prayers to God standing.</p>
                  <p>¶ This law is no where kept.</p>
                  <p>Let no Priest be made before 30 yeares, yea though he bee of an<note place="margin">The Counsell of Neocesario.</note> honest life, but let him tarry to the time appointed: for the Lord was baptized at 20 yeares and then preached.</p>
                  <p>¶ How this law is kept, the whole world may iudge, for the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of Loreine was made about the 12 yeare of his age. And Pope <hi>Clement</hi> made two of his Nephews Cardinals, being very boyes. And of late in the Popes Kingdome children haue bene made Archedea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, and Deanes of Cathedrall Churches.</p>
                  <p>No man may be receaued to baptisme in Lent, after two weekes.<note place="margin">The Counsell of Laodicia.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Bread ought not to be offered in lent but in the saturday and Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day.<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>¶ He speaketh of the bread of the holye Communion. But who keepeth these lawes.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:176462:22"/>
                  <p>Lay men ought not to sing any made and commonly vsed songs<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> in the Church, nor reade any booke beside the Canon: but onely the canonical bookes of the new and old testament, those bookes which ought to be read and receaued for authoritie, those bookes, which be deuided from the bookes called Apocripha, in the great Bible. Vnto the whiche Saint <hi>Ciprian, Hierome, Austen,</hi> with all the olde writers agree.</p>
                  <p>¶ But the third Counsell of <hi>Carthage</hi> added to these the bookes of Wisedome, Ecclesiasticus, Tobie, Iudith, Hester, and the Bookes of the Machabees, vnto which later Counsell, the Papistes cleaue with tooth and nayle, &amp; therevpon stay their purgatorie, praying to faints, with diuerse other errors and heresies: contrary to the elder and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter counsels. Hereby you may most easily perceaue, how shameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their generall counsels haue erred, as well in the iudgement of the Scriptures, as also in necessarie articles of our fayth and good maners. Yea and the chiefest and ouldest counsels be (as <hi>Anacharsis</hi> sayde of the lawes made by <hi>Solon</hi> for the <hi>Athenians</hi>) like to copwebs, wherein smal flies, gnats, and Miges be taken, and deuoured of the spiders: but great Hornettes and Humblebees flie through and breake them, without any daunger or hurt. And generally there is no lawes regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, kept or maintained among them: but suche as make (as they turne them) <hi>pro pane lucrando,</hi> that is, for their dignities, immunities or liberties and profites. Wherefore the wordes of our Sauiour Christ may be rightly verified of them: they lay heauie and importable bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens<note place="margin">Mat. 23.</note> on other mens shoulders, but will not once mooue them with their finger. For all their lawes be but nets to take and kill the poore fishes, and to fill their owne paun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:176462:23"/>
               <head>That nothing can be prooued by Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Aungels touching Religion. CAP. IIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Athan being chaunged into a Serpent, deceaued our first parents: and in them cast all mankinde headlong into<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> dampnation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Regum. 3. vlt.</hi> I will go foorth and bee a lying spirite in the mouth of all his Prophets. ¶ Reade the whole Chapter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Galath.</hi> 1. Though an Angell from Heauen preache anye other Gospell▪ &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Corrin. 2. cap.</hi> 11. Sathan himselfe is chaunged into an Aungell of light.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Colos.</hi> 2. Let no man make you shoote at a wrong marke, by the humblenesse and holinesse of Aungels.</p>
               <p>The same. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. The spirite speaketh euidently, that in the latter times some shall depart from the fayth, and shal giue heede vnto spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of error and diuelish doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4. Beleeue not euery spirite: but prooue the spirites, whether they are of God or not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 16. A certaine damsell, possessed with a spirite that prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sied, met vs: which brought her maister and mistresse much vaūtage with prophesiing. The same followed Paule and vs and cried, saying: these are the seruauntes of the most high God: which shewe vnto vs the way of saluatiō. And this did she many dayes: but Paule, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, turned about, and sayd to the spirite: I commaund thee, in the name of Iesu Christ, that thou come out of her. And he came out the same houre.</p>
               <p>Ciprian of the simplenesse of Prelates. The enemie (after the wordes of of the Apostles) chaunged himself into an Angell of light, and setteth foorth his seruauntes, as ministers of righteousnesse, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming<note place="margin">The Deuill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaueth man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he vvande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth from the vvord vvritten, and is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent therevvith.</note> night for day, death for health, desperacion vnder the coulour of hope, false fayth vnder the pretence of fayth, Antichrist vnder the name of Christ: so that whiles they counterfeite the like things, they make voyd the truth with subtiltie. This (dearely beloued bretheren) commeth to passe by this meanes, that we resort not to the originall of the truth, nor seeke the head Christ, nor keepe the doctrine of our
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:176462:23"/> heauenly maister.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ciprianus</hi> in his fourth treatise of the vanitie of Idols. Filthie spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites wandring abroade, being drowned in worldlye vices after they haue shronken from heauenlye vertue through worldlye corruption, being themselues destroyed, cease not to destroye other, and being infect with euill, infect other with the same.</p>
               <p>These inspire the hartes of the Prophets, euer lapping vp lies with the truth, they trouble mens liues, disquiet their sleepes, drawing their members awrye, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> their health, prouoke diseases, to force men to worshipping of them: &amp; this is the remedie of them when they cease to hurte: neyther haue they any other studie, but to call men back frō God, and turne them from the perceauing of true religion, to their su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition,<note place="margin">They hurte moste of all vvhen they cease from hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note> and seeing they be in payne themselfe, to seeke those to be companions of their payne, whome they haue made through their error, partakers of their sinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lactant▪ institutionū lib. 2. cap.</hi> 15. Corrupt &amp; damned spirites stray ouer al the world, &amp; seeke for ease of their destructiō, through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction<note place="margin">The Deuils vexe both bodye and soule, to cause men to seeke to them for helpe, and so to be vvorshipped as God.</note> of men. They therefore fill al the world with snares, fraudes, and errors, the which because they be fine spirits, and cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, conuey themselues into mens bodies, and being secretly hid within the body, trouble health, bring sicknes, fray mē with dreames, vex mens minds with sweat, that thorowe these harmes they maye force men to run to them for helpe. The cause of all which deceites, is darke to them that bee ignoraunt in the truth: for they thinke they profite when they cease from hurting, whiche canne doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but hurte. But they, whiche haue shrunken back from Gods seruice, because they be enemies and transgressors of the truth, goe about to chalenge to themselues the name and honour of God: not because they desire any honour (for what honour canne▪ the damned haue) nor that they should hurt God, who cannot be hurt: but to hurt men, whom they go about to draw away from the worship &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Gods true maiestie, least they shoulde attaine immortalitie, which they haue lost thorow their owne malice. So they couer all with darkenesse, and compasse the truth with cloudes: so that they cannot know their Lord, nor their father. And that they maye easilye alure men, they hide themselues in the churches, and are at hande in all sacrifices. Yea many times they worke miracles, through whiche<note place="margin">Sathan vvorketh miracles by Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and hereof springeth the vvorshipping of Images.</note> men, being astonied, doe giue to Images the fayth of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head. Hereof it commeth, that a Stone was cutte in sunder with a razure by a Sorcerer: and that <hi>Iuno of V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia</hi> aunswered,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:176462:24"/> that she would goe to Rome: and that a shippe folowed the hand of <hi>Claudia:</hi> and that <hi>Iuno</hi> being robbed, and <hi>Proserpina</hi> of <hi>Locrense,</hi> and <hi>Ceres</hi> of <hi>Milet,</hi> tooke vengeaunce of those that had committed sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: and <hi>Hercules</hi> of <hi>Appius,</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> of <hi>Atimus,</hi> and <hi>Minerua</hi> of <hi>Cesar.</hi> Hereof also it commeth, that a serpent deliuered the Citie of<note place="margin">The deuils speake in images as though they vvere Gods.</note>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> from the pestelēce, being brought from <hi>Epidaure.</hi> But cheefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they deceaue men in their Oracles and aunswers, whose Iuglinges vngodly men cannot discerne from the truth. Therefore they thinke, that Empires and victories, riches and luckye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unces of thinges, are giuen, of them: and to be short, oft times common welthes to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered<note place="margin">Though deuiles prophesi truely of things to come, yet all is but dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite, to make men to vvorship them.</note> from present daungers at their becke, whiche daungers they both declared by their aunswere, and being pacified with sacrifice, turned away. But al these be but deceites: for seing they know before, the disposition of God, because they were his ministers, they thrust themselues into these businesse, so that whatsoeuer thinges either be done, or haue bene done of God, they might seeme chefely to doe or haue done it.</p>
               <p>And so oft as any goodnesse is comming at hand to any people or Citie, according to Gods appointment, they promise that they will do it, eyther by myracles, dreames or reuelations: if Churches, if ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, if sacrifices, bee geuen to them. The which thinges being geuen, whan that chaunceth that needes muste bee: they get to<note place="margin">Sathan vnderpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of dead mens soules de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaueth them, that liue: and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them into Idolatry.</note> themselues great worshipe. For this cause bee temples vowed, for this cause be new Images halowed. And so oft as perilles be at hand, for some foolish and light cause they faine themselues angry: as <hi>Iuno</hi> towarde <hi>Varro.</hi> But these be the deceites of them, that lurking vnder the names of the dead, intend to plague them that be aliue. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whereas that daunger, that is at hand, maye bee auoyded: they would seeme that they, being pacified, haue turned it away.</p>
               <p>And if it cannot be eschewed, this they doe, that it mighte appeare to chaunce for the contempt of them: and so they purchase to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues great authoritye, and feare among men that know them not. Some men wil say, why doth god thē suffer these things neither doth he succour so euil errours? That euil things may fight with good, that vices may be contrary to vertues, that he may haue some whome hee may punish, and some whome he may honour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stapulensis</hi> vpon the. 2. <hi>Epistle</hi> to tbe <hi>Thessa. 2. Cap.</hi> Maruaile not of the counterfaite Aungels, and of the subtiltye of <hi>Sathan,</hi> resembling himselfe to Christ: seing we reade a like thing in the history of <hi>Hera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clides,</hi> of a monk called <hi>Valent.</hi> The deuil (saith he) chaūging himselfe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:176462:24"/> into the likenesse of our Sauiour, came to him by night with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie<note place="margin">Subtil Sathan fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth himselfe to be Christ and vvorshipped as God.</note> (as he fayned) of a thousand Angels: holding burning lampes in their handes, and with a fierie chariot, in the which he fayned our Sauiour to sit. Then one of them stept foorth and sayd thus vnto him: come foorth out of thy cell now, and doe nothing else but when thou seest him come a farre off, make hast to bow downe thy self and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship<note place="margin">Hovv shall vve then knovv any certaine truth by apparicions.</note> him, and so straight way returne againe to thine own house. Thē he went foorth out of his house, and beleeuing that he had seene that godly offices of heauenly ministers, and all shining with fierie lāpes, and Christ (as hee thought) himselfe not past a furlong off, fel flat vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">They that beleue visions often vvorship Sathan for Christ.</note> the ground, and worshipped him, whome he beleeued to bee the Lord. See here how this fearefull and foolish Monke <hi>Valent,</hi> leauing very Christ, worshipped Christes enemie: and in stead of the truth, a counterfet Antichrist and Sathan.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>That apparitions of the dead, be vnsuffiiciente to prooue truth. CAP. V.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen thou art come into the lande whiche<note place="margin">Deut. 18.</note> the Lorde thy God giueth thee, see that thou followe not the abhominacions of those nations: lette there not be founde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you any one, that maketh his sonne or daughter to goe through the fire, or that vseth witchcraft, or a chuser of dayes, and that regardeth the flying of Fouls, or a sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerer or a charmer, or that coūselleth with spirites, or a soothsayer, or that asketh the truth at them that be dead. For the Lord abhorreth all these: and for such abhominacions the Lord thy God doth caste them out before thee. But the Lord thy God, hath not suffered thee so to doe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Esay</hi> 8. And if they saye to you aske counsell at the Soothsayers, witches, charmers, and coniurers: then make them this aunswere: is<note place="margin">Reade the place.</note> there a people any where that asketh not counsell at his God? should men run vnto the dead for the liuing? If any man want light, let him looke vpon the lawe, and the testimonie, whether they speake after
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:176462:25"/> this meaning.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 16. If they heare not <hi>Mosis</hi> and the Prophets, neither will<note place="margin">Read the chapter</note> they beleeue, if one arise from death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lactantius</hi> in his institution <hi>lib. 2. cap.</hi> 2. The rude sorte thinke<note place="margin">He laugheth their foolishnes to scorne.</note> that mens soules walke about the graues, and reliques of theire bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chrysostome</hi> in his fourth Homilie of <hi>Lazarus.</hi> That thou mayest know that the doctrines of the scriptures and Prophets, are of more force, then if they that be raised from death shoulde tell any thing: consider this, that whosoeuer is dead, is a seruaūt. But what the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures<note place="margin">The Scripture ought to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued rather then the testimo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny of the dead: for it is Gods ovvne vvord, &amp; the other ofte times the deuils.</note> speake, the Lord himselfe speaketh: therefore though a deade man arise, yea although an Angell come downe from heauen, yet chiefly we ought to beleue the scriptures. For he that is master of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, &amp; Lord of the quick and the dead, made thē. If dead men should com again frō thēce vnto vs, the deuil might haue brought to vs false doctrines: &amp; that very easily. For he might haue shewed often tymes ghosts, &amp; haue suborned mē that shold coūterfeit death &amp; burial, and within a while after shew thēselues, as though they were raised again frō death, &amp; through thē to perswade the people so beguiled, what so euer him list. For if now, when no suche thing is done in deede, yet dreames seene of many men in their sleepe, as though it were of them that are departed hence, haue deceiued, destroyed, and ouerthrowne many men: much more it should haue chaunced, if the thing had bene done indeede, and gotten credite in mens minds (that is to say) if many of the deade had returned again to life, that wicked deuill would haue wrought innumerable deceits, and brought much fraude into the life of men. And for that cause God hath shut vp that waye,<note place="margin">The dead neuer returne after the death to tel their state that be dead.</note> neither doeth hee suffer any of the dead to come againe hether to tel what is done there: lest he by that meanes should bring in al his wiles and subtilties. For when there were Prophets, he stirred vp false pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: when the Apostles were false Apostles: when Christ appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he raised false Christes: when sounde doctrine was broughte in, he brought in corrupt doctrine, sowing cockle euery where. But God from whome nothing is hid, hath stopped his waye to those snares, and hee fauouring vs hath not suffered that any sonne at anye tyme<note place="margin">The Scripture is to be beleued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all thinges.</note> should come from thence hither, to tell what is there done to any mē liuing, teaching vs that we should rather beleeue the scriptures, then all other thinges.</p>
               <p>The same in <hi>Math. cap.</hi> 8. Homilie. 2. 9. I will not denie, but that menne haue bene killed of cursed charmers and Sorcerers: but
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:176462:25"/> that dead mennes soules worke with them, how shall they make me<note place="margin">It is not the soul of the dead that saith I am such a mans soule but the deuil counter feiteth the dead to deceue the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing: for soules departed the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy cannot vvalk here on earth.</note> beleeue that? because thou haste heard dead mens soules many times crye, I am the soule of such a one. Yea but these wordes procede out of the fraude and deceit of the deuill. For it is not the dead mans soule, that saith this, but the deuil that faineth this, that he may deceaue the hearers. For these ought to be taken as olde wiues fables, the wordes of lyars, and fraye bugges of children: neither can the soule, being departed from the body, walke in this earthe. For the soules of the righteous are in the hand of god, and the soules of sinners are straight after their death, caried away. Which is manifest by <hi>Lazarus</hi> and the riche man. The Lorde saythe also in another place: this day shall they fetche awaye thy soule. The soule therefore, after it be departed from the body, cannot wander here amongst vs. It may be prooued by many Scriptures, that the foules of the righteous cannot wander here after their death.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Stephen</hi> said, Lord receiue my spirite. And Paule desired to be losed from the body, and to be with Christ. Of the Patriarkes, also the Scripture saith, he was layd vp with his fathers, he dyed in a good age. And that the soules of sinners cannot tarry here with vs, harken to the riche man, what hee say the, consider what hee asketh, and obtaineth not. But if mens soules might be conuersant here, he would haue come as hee desired, and haue certified his brethren of the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in hell.</p>
               <p>Of the which place of Scripture it is manyfest, that after the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from the body, the soules are caried into a certaine place, from whence they cannot returne at their pleasure: but looke for that terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble day of iudgement.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hieron</hi> in the. 8. <hi>Ca.</hi> of <hi>Ieremy.</hi> If you doubt of any thing (saithe the prophet) know that it is written, that those nations, which the Lord shall scatter before thy face, shall harken to dreames and southsaiers: but the Lord thy god hath commaunded thee not so to doe, but if you wil know things that be doubtful, giue your selues rather to the testy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the law and the Scriptures. But if youre congregation will not search the word of the Lord: they shall not haue the light of the truth but shall wander in darkenes of errors. You ought to know this, that euery nation asketh counsel at their own Gods, and enquireth of the dead for the health of the quick: but God hath giuen you the law for your healpe, so that you may say, the southsaying of the heathen, which deceiue their worshippers, is not like ours: which is spoken out of the lawe, without any cost.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:176462:26"/>
               <p>Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> also sayeth, that the spirite of <hi>Samuell</hi> whiche the woman sorcerer raised to <hi>Saul,</hi> was not the soule of <hi>Samuell,</hi> but the Diuell which appeared in <hi>Samuels</hi> likenesse, for to deceiue <hi>Saul:</hi> this doeth he prooue both by euydent Scriptures, and strong rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>Neyther are Myracles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to prooue oure faith. CAP. VI.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He wise men and enchaunters of <hi>Pharao,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 7. 8.</note> turned their roddes into serpentes, and the waters of <hi>Aegipt</hi> into blood: and made al the whole lande to swarme with frogges, through their sorceries.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. If there arise among you, a Prophet, or a dreamer of Dreames, &amp; giue thee a signe or a wonder, and that signe or wonder, which he hath said, come to passe, and then say: let vs go after straunge gods, which thou hast not knowne, and let vs serue them: Hearken not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wordes of that Prophet, or dreamer of dreames. For the Lorde thy God tempteth thee, to wit whether ye loue the Lorde your God, with all your harts, and all your soules.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hieremie</hi> 23. Behold here am I, sayth the Lord, against those Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets that dare prophesie lies, and deceiue my people with their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and miracles, whome I neuer sent, nor commaunded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 7. Many shall say to me in those dayes, Lord, haue wee not prophesied in thy name? haue we not cast out Diuels in thy name? &amp; then it shall be aunswered them: I neuer knew you, depart from mee you children of iniquitie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 12. An euill and froward generation seeketh a signe, and there shall no signe bee giuen to them, but the sign of <hi>Jonas</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 24. There shall arise false Christes, and false Prophets, and shal shew great miracles, and wonders in so much that, if it were pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible,<note place="margin">Mar. 13.</note> euen the very elect should be deceaued: but take you heede, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:176462:26"/> I haue shewed you all thinges before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thessa.</hi> 2. The comming of that wicked one (meaning Antichrist) shall be after the working of Sathan with all lying power, signes and wonders, and with all deceit of vnrighteousnesse of them, that shall perishe because they receiued not the loue of the trueth, that they might be saued. And therefore God shall sende them strong delusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they might beleeue lies: that all they mighte bee damned, which beleeued not the truth, but had pleasure in vnrighteousnesse.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Act. 8. Simon Magus,</hi> an inchaunter, by his wonders bewitched the <hi>Samaritanes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Act. 13. Elimas</hi> the sorceror had of long time deceiued the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochians.</hi> Reade the stories.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Irenae. lib.</hi> 1. telleth of a certaine Iudge called <hi>Marke,</hi> whiche in<note place="margin">By this example ye may iudge of the popish mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles.</note> the sacrament of thankes giuing wonderfullye deceaued the simple people. For he so chaunged the colour of wine, that it appeared vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be blood: and a little wine so increased through his iugling, that the chalice was filled, and ranne ouer. By this iugling it is playne y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, that those myracles that be alleaged of many men for the real presence in the sacrament of the alter, doe not confirme their error, but be very delusions of the deuill or of his iugling ministers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chrisostome</hi> in his 49. Homilie vpon the 24 of <hi>Math.</hi> Afore tyme it was knowne whiche were true Christen men and whiche false by myracles: but how were the false knowne? Because they could not work, such or like miracles as true christen mē did: but they wrought vaine thinges, making men to wonder, but bringing no profite at al. But the Christians did miracles, which not only brought wonders, but also profite: and by these they were knowne, whiche were true Christians, and which false. But now working of miracles is vtterlye taken away. Yea counterfeit miracles are rather found among them, that be false christians: as <hi>Peter</hi> declareth in <hi>Clement.</hi> Antichrist shal haue full power giuen him, to worke great miracles.</p>
               <p>The same in his first Oration against the Iewes, vpon this place of <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. If there arise among you a prophet or a dreamer of dreames &amp;c. That, that he sayth (sayth <hi>Chrisostome</hi>) is this: if any Prophet saye,<note place="margin">God suffreth vvicked men to vvorke mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles for the triall of the faithfull.</note> I can raise a dead man, and giue sight to a blinde man, obey me, let vs worship Deuils, let vs doe sacrifice to Idols: more ouer if a man speake thus, that he can giue the blinde his sight, raise the deade, yea though he doe these thinges, beleeue him not. For the Lorde trying thee suffreth him to doe them, not that he knew not thy mynde, but to giue thee occasion of triall whether thou loue God indeede.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:176462:27"/>
               <p>The same in <hi>Iohn cap.</hi> 2: In the ende of the 22. Hom. There be some<note place="margin">The faithfull neede no mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, for signs are giuen to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeuers. 1. Cor. 14.</note> doubtlesse now adayes, that aske why men worke no miracles now. If thou be faythfull as thou oughtest to bee, if thou loue Christ, as hee should be loued, thou needest no miracles: for signes are giuen to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeuers, and not to the faithfull.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Augustine</hi> against <hi>Faustus</hi> the <hi>Manachee, lib. 13. cap.</hi> 5. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that be stablished and set foorth by so great authoritie, yee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spice: miracles you work none: which though you did, yet we would beware of you, by the Lord instructing and teaching vs, saying: there shall arise false Christs. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The same of the citie of God, <hi>lib. 20. cap.</hi> 19. The presence of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ shall be after the working of Sathan, with al lying powers, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. For then shall Sathan be let lose, and by him Antichrist, with all his power shal work maruailously but lyingly: of the which miracles it was wont to be doubted, whether they be called lying signes and wonders for this cause that hee shall deceaue mans sences with visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, so that he seemeth to doe the thing that he doeth not in deede, or else because the same, although they bee true miracles and not counterfeit, yet they draw men to beleeue that they cannot be done, but by the power of God: whereas men know not the power of the Deuill: chiefly seing that how great soeuer power he hath, hee hath receiued it. For when fire fel downe from heauen, and with one dash destroyed so great a familie with so many heardes of cattell of holye <hi>Iob,</hi> and a sodaine whirlewind ouerthrowing his house, slew his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: these were no deceaueable visions, but for euery one of these it is sayd: they shall be beguiled with signs and wonders, that shal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue to be beguiled, for so much as they haue not receiued the loue of the truth, that they might be saued. Neyther did the Apostle, feare to say and adde: God shall sende them strong delusions, that they should beleeue lies. For God doth sende these things, because he suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freth the Deuill to doe them: he indeede by his iust iudgemente, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the deuill doth it of a wicked and malicious purpose.</p>
               <p>The same of the vnitie of the Church, <hi>cap.</hi> 16. Let them shew their Church, if they can, not in the sayinges and in the fame of the Affri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canes, not in rhe determinations of their Bishoppes, not in any mans reasoninges, not in false signes and wonders (for agaynste all this wee bee warned and armed by Gods worde) but in the thinges ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted in the lawe, spoken afore by the Prophets, in the songs of the Psalmes, in the voyce of the sheaphearde himself, &amp; the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinges and painfulnesse of the Euangelistes, that is in the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:176462:27"/> of the bookes Canonicall: but not so that they maye gather and<note place="margin">All doctrine ought to be tried by the canonicall in plaine sence: &amp; not by vvords, that be darke, doubtfull or figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue.</note> rehearse those thinges, that be spoken darkely and doubtfully and figuratiuely, which euery man may vnderstand as he list after his own mind. For such things cānot be vnderstanded and expounded right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, except those thinges, that be very plainly spoken, be perceaued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with a constant faith. Let him not say this is true, because I say it, or because my companion sayth thus, or these my companions, or these our Bishopes, Clearkes, or lay men: or else, it is true, because<note place="margin">Miracles shevved at the tombes of saintes prooue no doctrine.</note> such miracles did <hi>Donatus, Pontius,</hi> or whatsoeuer other: or else be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause men praye at the tombes of our dead menne, and bee heard: or because these and these thinges chaunced there: or that this brother of ours, or this sister of ours saw such a vision: ether waking, or sleping<note place="margin">Visions seene ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in dreames or being avvake cannot make any doctrine.</note> in his dreame, saw such a vision or sight: away with these. Either they be fayninges of lying men, or the wonders of deceitfull deuils. For either they are not true, that are spoken: or if any miracles de done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong heretiques, we ought the more to take heede of them, because that when the Lord had said there should come some, that by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king diuerse miracles should deceiue, if it were possyble, the very e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect: he added, and earnestly setting foorth the thing said: behold, I haue told you before.</p>
               <p>Whereof the Apostle, admonishing them, speaketh plainly: that in the latter times menne shoulde departe from the faythe, geuing heede to spirites of errour, and doctrines of deuils. Furthermore if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny<note place="margin">Men be heard at the tombes of he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>retikes and yet is not their doctrin true.</note> man bee heard praying at the tombes of heretiques he receaueth, whether it be good or euill not for the merite of the place, but for the rite of his desire. For the spirite of the Lord, as it is written, filleth the whole world, and the earnest eare heareth all thinges, and many be heard of God when he is angry, of whome the Apostle sayth; he had giuen them vp to their harts desier. And god to many, whom he fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, giueth not what they would, that he may giue them that which is profitable: wherfore saith the same Apostle of the sting of his flesh, the messenger of Sathan (which he said was geuen him to buffet him least he should be exalted aboue measure by the greatnes of reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) for the which I praied the lord thrise, that he would take it away from me, and hee said vnto me: my grace is sufficient for thee, for my strength is made perfect through weakenesse. Doe we not read that many mē were heard of god hiselfe in the high places of Iury? which high places neuertheles so displeased god, that kings which distroied thē were not blamed, &amp; kings that destroied them were praised. But this ought to be vnderstād, that the desier of him, that praieth, is more
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:176462:28"/> worthie or of more strength, then the place of prayer: but of false vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions let them reade what is written, both that Sathan doth chaunge<note place="margin">The diuell vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth miracles in the temples and Idols of the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils although their religion be false and detesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> himselfe into an Angell of light, and that their dreames haue decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued many men: lette them also heare what the heathen tell of theire temples and Gods, wonderfully eyther done or seene, and yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse the Gods of the heathen be deuils, but the Lorde made the heauens. Therefore many men be heard and after many diuers sorts, not only Catholick christians, but also Panims, and Iewes and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes giuen to diuerse errors and superstitions: doubtlesse they are heard either of deceitfull spirites, whiche neuerthelesse doe nothing except they be permitted of God highly and vnspeakeablye, iudging what is meete to be giuen to euery man, or else of God himselfe ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the punishmēt of malice, or the comfort of miserie, or for the admonishment of eternall saluation. But to that eternall saluatiō cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth no man, but he that hath the head Christ, yea and no man can haue the head Christ, which is not in his body the Churche, whiche Church, like as the head it self, we must know in the canonicall scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and not to seeke it in diuers rumours and opinions of men, not in facts, sayinges and sights. &amp;c. Let al this sort of them be chaffe, and not giue sētence afore hand against the wheat, if they be the Church: but whether they be the Church, let them shewe none other wayes but by the Canonicall bookes of the holy scriptures. For neyther doe we say that men ought to beleeue vs, because we are in the catholick church of Christ, or because <hi>Optaius</hi> bishop of <hi>Miliuet,</hi> or <hi>Ambrose</hi> Bishop of <hi>Milaine,</hi> or that innumerable other bishops of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation doe allow this doctrine that we keepe, or because in chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of our companions it is preached or else because that through the whole world in those holy places, where our congregations re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort, so many wonders either of hearinges or of healinges be done: so that bodies of martirs, being hid so many yeares (whiche if they will aske, they may learne of many) were shewed to <hi>Ambrose:</hi> or that at those bodies a certaine man, being many yeres blinde, well knowne to the whole Citie of <hi>Miliane,</hi> receiued his eyes and his sight: or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he being in a dreame did see, or he being rapte in spirite didde heare, eyther that he should not goe to the part of the <hi>Donatists,</hi> or that they should depart from their opinion. Whatsoeuer such things be done in the catholicke Church, the Church is not therefore proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued catholick because these be done in it. The Lorde Iesus himselfe, when he was risen from death, and offred his own body to bee seene with the eyes, and handled with the handes of his Apostles, lest they
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:176462:28"/> should then think themselues to be deceiued, he rather iudged that they ought to bee stablyshed by the witnesses of the lawe, prophetes and psalmes shewing those thinges to be fullfilled in him, that were spoken so long before: so hee set foorth his church, bidding repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce and forgeuenes of sinnes to be preached in his name, through all nations, beginning at <hi>Jerusalem.</hi> That these thinges be written in the law and Prophetes, himselfe witnesseth: this is set out by word of mouth. These are the doctrines, these are the stayes of our cause. we read written in the Actes of the Apostles of some faithfull men, that they searched the Scriptures whether they were so. What Scriptures I pray you, but the Canonicall of the law and the Prophets? to these are ioyned the Gospels, the Apostles Epistles, the Actes of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, and the <hi>Apocalipsis</hi> of Sainct <hi>John.</hi> Search al these, bring foorth some plaine thing, whereby you maye declare that the Church hath remained onely in <hi>Affricke:</hi> or that this (which the Lord saith shall come to passe: This Gospell shal be preached to all the worlde for a testimonie to all nacions) shalbe verified of <hi>Affricke.</hi> But bring out somewhat, that needeth none interpreter: you may not be conuinced that the things, which is spoken of another matter, you goe about to wrest to your purpose.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chrysostome</hi> of the contricion of the harte. Christe promysed not<note place="margin">Not miracle vvorkers, but the commaundment▪ keepers, are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led blessed of Christ.</note> that hee woulde rewarde at the latter daye them that worke signes and wonders, but them that keepe his commaundementes, saying: come you blessed Chyldren of my Father, receaue that Kingdome, whiche was prepared for you from the beginning of the world: Hee saide not because you did miracles, but because I was hungry &amp;c. he shal also cal them blessed, not that wrought miracles but the humble and meke in hart.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ciril</hi> in <hi>John lib. 7, cap.</hi> 13. To worke miracles maketh not a man one whit more holy, seing that it is also common to euil men and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, as the Lord himselfe also witnesseth: many shall say to me in that day &amp;c. And contrariwise working of no miracles hindereth not a mans holynesse. For <hi>Iohn</hi> wrought neither signe nor miracle: and yet was this no derogacion to his holynesse. For among the children of women there was none greater then he.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sabellic</hi> vpon the life of <hi>Celestine</hi> almoste fiue hundreth yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<note place="margin">This vvould bee▪ put among the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paricions of the dead. Sathan coonter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiteth Moses.</note> Christ, the deuill taking vpon him the person of <hi>Moyses,</hi> shewed himselfe visibly in the syght of the Iewes, that dwelt at <hi>Candie:</hi> promysing that hee woulde bring them againe into the land of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myse, where <hi>Jerusalem</hi> standeth drye footed, the waters standing
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:176462:29"/> on eyther side in maner of a wal, as when the children of Israell were brought out of the land of <hi>Aegipt.</hi> Many of the Iewes rashlye giuing credite to these iuglinges, &amp; entring into the sea, were ouerwhelmed with the waues thereof: except a few, the which at last, being war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of their vanitie, became Christians.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Custome also is of no strength in this case of proouing a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. CAP. VII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Xodi.</hi> 23. Follow not the multitude to doe euill.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leuiticus.</hi> 18. The Lorde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth the Israelytes not to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the custome of the <hi>Aegiptians:</hi> nor the <hi>Cananites.</hi> Reade the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ezechiell.</hi> 20. Walke not in the statutes of your forefathers, and keepe not their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunces: and defile not your selues with their Idols.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Regum. 4. cap.</hi> 17. Vnto this daye they keepe their olde customes, they feare not God nor doe after his customes, ordinaunces and lawes.</p>
               <p>The same. They did not hearken vnto the Lord: but did after their old custome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 9. They followed the wickednesse of their own hearts, and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued strange gods, as their fathers taught them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> of virginitie or prayses. Custome for the most parte ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his beginning either of ignoraunce or simplicitie, in processe of time waxeth strong by vse: and so it is alleaged againste the truth. Whatsoeuer smelleth against the truth, that is heresie, yea though it be olde custome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ciprian</hi> vnto <hi>Cicilie lib. 2. Epistola.</hi> 3. There is no cause, why (deare brother) that anye man shoulde thinke the custome of some men oughte to bee followed. If any man haue thought that onely water oughte to bee offred in the Chalice: wee must firste aske whome
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:176462:29"/> they followed: and that Christ only ought to be heard the father wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesseth from heauen, saying: this is my welbeloued sonne, heare him. Wherfore if only Christ ought to be heard, we oughte not to regarde what any man afore vs thought to be done, but what Christ, which is before, did first: neither ought we to follow the custome of man, but the truth of God.</p>
               <p>The same to <hi>Iulian.</hi> of the baptising of hereticks, in vaine do some men, when they be ouercome with the truth, alleage custom against vs: as though custome were greater then the truth. S. <hi>Augustine</hi> hath the same.</p>
               <p>The same to <hi>Pompus</hi> against <hi>Steuens</hi> Epistle. Custome withoute truth, is an old errour: for the which cause, let vs leaue custome, and follow the truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chrisostome</hi> vpon Genesis 29. Homilie 59. For if the Counsell bee good and profitable, yea though it be not custome, keepe it: But if it be hurtfull and noysome cast it away. For if we will be wise and care for our saluation, we may leaue of an euill custome &amp; bring in a good custome: and so shall we giue no small occasion to them, that come after vs, to chaunge the same, and haue the rewarde of those thinges, that be done of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jerome</hi> in his Preface to <hi>Job.</hi> Olde custome is of suche force, that vices, whiche many themselues confesse, please them through it.</p>
               <p>The same <hi>cap.</hi> 9. Neither are the errours of our fathers, nor our el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to be followed, but the authoritie of the scriptures: and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of God that teacheth vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Augustine</hi> of one only baptisme, <hi>lib. 2. distinct. 8. cap.</hi> When the truth is once knowne, lette custome giue place to the trueth. For who doubteth, but custome oughte to giue place to the manifeste truth.</p>
               <p>The same in the same place. Let no man preferre Custome aboue truth and reason. For truth and reason doe euer exclude cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorius</hi> to <hi>Guelmunde</hi> the Bishop. 2. <hi>distinct. Si consuetudo.</hi> If thou chaunce to lay custome against me, thou must take heede what the Lord sayth: I am the way, the truth and the life. He did not say: I am custome, but the truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicolas</hi> the Pope to <hi>Ignatius</hi> the reuerende Bishop, 8. <hi>Distinct.</hi> An euill custome is no lesse to be auoyded, then an hurtfull corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: which except it be plucked vp the sooner by the rootes: it will be
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:176462:30"/> taken of the vngodly for a law.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>Reasons againste Vnwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Ʋerities. CAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He olde Testament was sufficient for the Iewes: and why shall not both the newe and old suffice vs?</p>
               <p>Christ and the Apostles proued al their doctrines, by the Law &amp; Prophets. What an arrogancie is it then in vs, to teach any thing whiche wee can neyther prooue by the law, the prophets, the Apostles, nor the Euangelists.</p>
               <p>The deuill, when hee tempted Christe, was not so farre past all shame to perswade any thing withoute the testimonie of the Scriptures, although hee did (as his deare children, the Papistes doe) falslye alleage them, wrest them from their true meaning to a contrarye sence, and also cutte off that, which should make agaynst him, or declare the true meaning of the scriptures.</p>
               <p>This word (vnwritten verities) is a new tearm lately inuented and now here heard or read among the old writers: of which they could not haue ben ignorant, if there had ben any suche thing needefull to saluation.</p>
               <p>Al contention which the old Fathers had with heretickes, was for the scriptures: which heretickes partly denied, as <hi>Marcion, Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus</hi> and <hi>Faustus:</hi> partly they wronglye expounded: but for thinges which are not contained in the scriptures, they neuer accused anye man of heresie.</p>
               <p>If there were any word of God beside the scripture, we coulde ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be certaine of gods worde: and if we be vncertain of gods word, the Deuill mighte bring in among vs a newe worde, a newe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, a newe fayth, a newe Churche, a newe God, yea him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to be God, as he hath alreadie done in the popishe kingdome. For this is the foundation of Antichristes kingdome to settle himself
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:176462:30"/> in Gods Temple, which is the heart and conscience of man: of him to be feared and worshipped, as though he were God himselfe.</p>
               <p>If the Church and the Christian fayth did not stay himselfe vppon the worde of God certaine, as vpon a sure and strong foundation: no man could know whether he had a right fayth, and whether he were in the true Church of Christ, or in the sinagog of Sathan.</p>
               <p>If we be bound to beleeue certaine thinges, deliuered from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles by word of mouth only, without writing, as they would make vs beleeue (but what those things be no man can tell) It should here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of follow, that we are bound to beleeue we wote not what.</p>
               <p>Without fayth it is not possible to please God: and faith commeth by hearing of Gods word. Ergo where Gods word lacketh, there can be no fayth.</p>
               <p>Almightie God afore he gaue to <hi>Moses</hi> the law written of the ten commaundements, wherein he fully taught the true worshipping of him as it were a preseruatiue against a plague or a poyson to come: gaue them this notable lesson, worthy alway to be had in memorye: you shall adde nothing to the wordes &amp;c. and againe he often times repeateth the same sentence both in the law and the Prophets, in the gospels, and the Epistles of the Apostles. And because his people should neuer forget it, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> commaundeth the same in the last wordes of all the new testament, threatning terrible plagues (that is) the losse of his euerlasting ioyes of heauen, and the payne of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall fire of hell, to all them, that eyther put too or take ought from the worde of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:176462:31"/>
               <head>Scriptures alleaged by the Papistes for vnwritten Verities, with aunsweres to the same. CAP. IX.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here two or iij. be gathered in my name,<note place="margin">Math. 18.</note> ther am I in the middest of thē. But Christ cannot erre: for he is the truth it selfe: ergo they cannot erre in their Synodes, conuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, and generall counsels, being ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered togither in his name.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunsvvere. </seg>
                  </label> Christ sayd, when two or three bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in my name, &amp;c. and to bee gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in his name, is in our assēblies to seeke his only glory &amp; not ours, to doe all things by his prescript word. For not euery one that sayeth vnto me, Lord Lord, shall enter &amp;c. As witches, charmers, necromansers, and coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rars,<note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> vse their wicked artes all in the name of God and Christ: and yet is not Christ with them. For the sixe sonnes of <hi>Sceua,</hi> the chiefe Priest of the Iewes, went about to cast out euill spirites in the name of Iesus, whome Paule preached: but yet Christ was not with them, but the<note place="margin">Actes. 19.</note> wicked spirite, which wounded them, and draue them away naked. Moreouer all forgers of wiles, counterfeiters of false instrumentes, and iudges giuing false sentences, in the ecclesiasticall law, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with this glorious title: in the name of god, Amen. Therfore sprāg this olde Prouerbe, in the name of God beginneth all mischiefe: and yet Christ is with none of these, though they pretende to doe al these<note place="margin">Mathevv. 7.</note> things in his name, christ saith also, many shal prophesie in my name and cast out Diuels, &amp; worke miracles in my name, &amp; then wil I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse to them, that I neuer knew you. Reade <hi>Eusebius</hi> and <hi>Athanasius,</hi> and you shall there see, what pride, contention, hatred, malice, enuie, &amp; desire, to beare rule, reigned in the counsels of the cleargie at those dayes, not much past 400 yeres after Christ. What thinke you they<note place="margin">A replication.</note> would say, if they saw our counsels, where the Romishe Antichrist triumpheth? no doubt, that, though an Angell frō heauen preach any other &amp;c. Here you will replie agayne: Christ sayth where 2 or 3. are
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:176462:31"/>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunsvvere. </seg>
                  </label> gathered &amp;c. Nowe in euery counsell are not onely. 2. or. 3. learned and Godly men, but many. Ergo they cannot erre. I graunt that in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery generall counsel be many good men, which do not erre, nor are deceiued: &amp; yet it foloweth not that the whole councel cannot erre.</p>
               <p>For in councels the more parte is taken for the whole, and thinges be there determined and ordered, not by reason, learning, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the word of God: but by stoutnesse, wilfulnesse and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of the more parte. In those counsels, where be mo euil and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, then good and godly, it commeth often times to passe, that iniquitie hauing the vpper hande, the greater part ouercommeth the better: and yet the good men neither erre, nor consent to these errors concluded by the wicked and the more parte, but resist and speake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them to the vtmoste of their power not without great daunger of their liues, yea and somtimes it costeth them their liues in deede, as it is now dayly seene.</p>
               <p>The Scribes and the Pharises sit vpon <hi>Moses</hi> seate, whatsoeuer<note place="margin">Math. 23. The. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. argument.</note> they bid you do, that do, but after their workes doe not: for they say and doe not. Here (they say) it appeareth plainly, that christ comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs to obaye the heades of the church, how euill soeuer their liues be.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The first ansvvere</note> First let them looke well what maner men they make themselues, that is, Scribes and Pharises the greatest enemies of God, persecutors and murtherers of his Prophetes, of the Apostles, and of Christ him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, and so Antichristes. <note place="margin">The second auns<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvere.</note> Secondly <hi>Moses</hi> seate is not his office or authority, but his doctrine: and therefore sayth Sainct <hi>Augustine,</hi> that seate which is his doctrine, suffereth them not to erre, and in a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nother place, they sitting in <hi>Moses</hi> seate teache the lawe of God, therefore God teacheth by them. But if they will teache their owne doctrine, beleue them not: for suche seeke their owne and not Iesus Christes: and Christe biddeth vs beware of the leuen of the Pharises, and then the disciples knew that he spake not of the leuen of breade but of their doctrines, although they sat in <hi>Moses</hi> seate, if they will needes contend, the dignitie or office of <hi>Moses,</hi> to be <hi>Moses</hi> seate, and yet erred shamefully in their doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The fourth argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Math. 28.</note> Behold, I am with you all the daies vnto the worldes end: this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise was not made to the Apostles only (for they dyed shortly after Christ) but to the Church. Ergo the Church cannot erre.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunsvvere. </seg>
                  </label> I Beseeche them to beginne a littell afore, and they shall plainely heare Christ himselfe vnlose this knotte. The words before are these in <hi>Marke:</hi> goe and preache my Gospell to euery creature, and in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:176462:32"/>
                  <hi>Mathew,</hi> goe and teache all people, baptising them in the name of the father, of the sonne. &amp;c. teaching them to obserue all thinges, whatsoeuer I haue commaunded you: and lo, I will be with you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the worlds ende. Here you may see this promise of Christ, I will be with you &amp;c. is not absolute or vniuersall, but giuen vnder a condici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (that is) if you preache my Gospell truely, if you baptise rightlye, if you teache the baptized to doe all thinges, that I haue commaunded you: lo, then I wil be with you vnto the worlds end. But if you teache any other Gospell, or baptise otherwise, or bid them doe any other thing, aboue that which I haue commaunded you, you haue no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise of God, but the curse, that Paule threatneth: though wee or an Aungell from heauen preache. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The. 5. argument Iohn. 16.</note> I haue yet many moe things to say vnto you, but you cannot beare thē away now, howbeit whē he is come, which is the spirite of truth, hee will leade you into all truth. Here you may see (sayth the enemies of Gods truth) that Christ taught not all thinges himselfe, but lefte many thinges to be taught to the disciples, by the holy ghost after his death.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunsvvere. </seg>
                  </label> Christ sayth not, I haue many thinges to say, whiche I will not tell you now, but which you cannot beare now. That is, you cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue<note place="margin">Iohn. 14.</note> or vnderstand them now: and thus Christ himself expoundeth these wordes, the comforter, which is the holy ghost, whome my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will send in my name: he shall teache you all thinges, and put you in remembraunce of all thinges, that I haue sayd vnto you, and no new or other thinges. For Christ sayth plainly that he himself had<note place="margin">Iohn. 15.</note> taught them all before, saying: all thinges, that I haue hearde of my father, haue I opened vnto you.</p>
               <p>Moreouer our sauiour in plaine words sheweth what things those were, that his disciples could not vnderstande, although hee manye times tolde them the same before. Behold sayth he, we go vp to <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke. 18.</note> and all shall be fulfilled, that are written by the Prophets of the sonne of man. For he shall be deliuered to the Gentils, and shall bee mocked, and despitefullye entreated, and spitted on, and when they haue scourged him, they will put him to death, and the thirde day he will rise againe: and they vnderstoode none of these thinges. For these sayinges were hid from them so, that they perceiued none of the things, that were spoken: although he spake to them in moste playne tearmes. And the cause, why they perceiued not his so playne speech, was this. They wer yet carnal &amp; vnderstood the prophesies of Christs kingdom carnally thinking that Christ shold raign at Ierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:176462:32"/> like a mightie conquerour, and subdewe all the Gentiles vnder<note place="margin">Math. 20.</note> the yoke of bondage to the Iewes, so that the Iewes should be Lords and rulers ouer all the world for euer. And therefore <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> asked a peticion of Iesus by their mother, that they, her two sonnes, might sit the one on his right hand, and the other on his left hand, in his Kingdome: and when he spake of his death, <hi>Peter</hi> toke him aside and rebuked him saying: Maister fauour thy selfe, this shall not hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen<note place="margin">Math. 16.</note> vnto the, to whome Christ said, go after me Sathan. These be the thinges, that the disciples could not then beare or vnderstande, but thought that he had spoken some alegory, ridle or darke speeche vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: but after his resurrection, he opened their wittes that they might vnderstand the Scriptures, and saide vnto them: thus it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and thus it behoued Christ to suffer. And to the two disciples go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Emaus,</hi> hee expounded <hi>Moses,</hi> the Prophetes and all the Scriptures, that were written of him. And after the ascension the holy ghoste appeared to them in fierie tongues, and filled them with all knowledge, and they began to speake with sundry tongues, as the holy ghost gaue them vtterance: and then they vnderstode the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures perfectly.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 6. argument Iohn. 21.</note> Many other tokens did Iesus, which are not written in this booke. Again, there are many other things, that Iesus did, which, if they were writted, I suppose, the world should not be able to contain the bokes, that should be written.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunsvvere. </seg>
                  </label> S. <hi>Iohn</hi> speaketh not here of fayth and charitie but of mirracles, the knowledg whereof is not necessary for our saluation, as his words folowing doe declare: these are written, that you might beleeue, that Iesus is Christ, the sonne of God, and in beleuing may haue life in his name. And what is more required or desired of a Christian, then to enioye euerlasting lyfe? that ought to bee our whole study and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, to that end ought we to apply all our mindes, words workes and prayers.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. Thess. 2. argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Stand fast brethren, and keepe the ordinaunces, that ye haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned either by our preaching or by our Epistle. Of these wordes they gather, that Paule taught diuerse things to the <hi>Thessalonians</hi> by word of mouth, without writing: whiche neuerthelesse he commaunded them to obserue and doe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunsvvere. </seg>
                  </label> I Graunt that Paule taught manye thinges by worde of mouthe whiche hee wrotte not in his Epistles to the <hi>Thessalonians.</hi> But how shal they proue, that the same things be neither written by him in any other of his Epistles, nor in any other place of the holy Byble?
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:176462:33"/> For what argument is this? it is not written in this place or to those persons, ergo it is not written in the scripture at all. For the shortnesse of one Epistle, or of one Sermon, cannot sufficiently contayn al things necessarie for our saluation: and therefore be there so manye bookes of the Scripture, that what so is omitted, &amp; not spoken of in one place or else darkely spoken of, might be written plainely in another place. And for this cause S. Paule writeth to the Coloss. saying: when this letter is red with you, cause it also to be read to the Laodicians. And reade you also the Epistle written from Laodicia. And S. Paule wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth<note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.</note> of himselfe, such as we are in our absence by letters, such are wee indeede being presēt. Moreouer Paule speaketh not here of doctrins of faith and charitie, which euer continew without changing, adding or minishing, but of certaine traditions, obseruations, ceremonies &amp; outward rites and bodily excerciscs, which (as he sayth) is little worth to Godward, but to be vsed for comlinesse, decent order and vnifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie in the Church, and to auoyd schisme: which ceremonies euery good man is bounde to keepe, least he trouble the commō order, and so breake the order of charitie in offending his weake brethren, so long as they be approoued, receiued, and vsed by the heades &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon consent. But they and euery one of such ceremonies, as be ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sacraments, nor commaundements of fayth and charitie, maye be altered and chaunged, and othr set in their places, or else vtterlye taken away by the authoritie of Princes, and other their rulers &amp; sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects in the church. Yea also the traditions, made by the Apostles in<note place="margin">Actes. 15.</note> full counsell at Ierusalem, may be, and already are taken away: as to abstaine from thinges offred vnto Images, from blood and strangled are no where kept. And this of Paule, that a man should neither pray nor preache capped, or with his head coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, is also cleane aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:176462:33"/>
               <head>Doctours to the same pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose with their aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sweres. CAP. X.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ertullian</hi> of the crown of a soldior. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing many traditions (as to renounce the Deuill, his pompe and his Angels afore Baptisme, to dip the Children thrise in the Font, to giue it pappe of honie and milke first thing after Baptisme, and not to wash it in a whole weeke after, to offer both at the daye of Buriall and byrth, on the Sondaye neyther to faste nor to praye kneeling, nor also from Easter to Whitsontide, crossing of our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heades, with diuerse such like) sayth: if thou require a lawe of these and other such disciplines, there can be no pretence of a law for them out of the scriptures. But thou shalt either perceiue by thy self, or learn of some other, that perceaueth it: that custome being authour, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmer, conseruer and obseruer of fayth, shall maintaine and defende the cause of this tradition and custome of fayth.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunsvvere. </seg>
                  </label> By the scriptures before alleaged it is euidently prooued, that all thinges, requisite for our saluation, be set foorth in the holy bookes of the bible, and that it is not lawful to put any thing thereto, vnder pain of euerlasting damnation. The same <hi>Tertullian</hi> also, as it is rehearced, sayth that, there is nothing else, that oughte to bee beleeued after<note place="margin">Vnderstand heere as necessaay to saluation.</note> Christs Gospell once published. Yea all the old authours, a thousand yeare after Christ, and likewise, almost, all the new, affirme the same: and would not haue vs credite their sayinges without the proofe of Gods word.</p>
               <p>Why should we then beleeue <hi>Tertullian</hi> against so playne Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, against the olde Fathers of the Church, and also contrarie to his owne sayinges? Yet here will I gentlye interprete him, so as hee maye both agree with the Scriptures, with the olde Authoures, and also with himself: <hi>Tertullian</hi> speaketh heare not of doctrines of fayth hope and charitie: but of traditions, outward gestures, rites and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:176462:34"/> ceremonies, which be not necessarie for our saluation: but be ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for a decent order, and conformitie in the church, as is plainlye shewed in the aunswere to Saint Paule in the Epistle to the Thessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians. And that hee speaketh of such rites and ceremonies it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident. For all those that he rehearseth bee meere ceremonies, and few of them kept at this day▪ which no man might haue altered or abolished, if they had bene necessarilie to be kept, vnder payne of dā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>Ciprian</hi> to <hi>Pompeius</hi> against <hi>Stephans</hi> Epistle. It is of no lesse autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie that the Apostles deliuered by the instruction of the holy ghost, then that which Christ himselfe deliuered.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunsvvere. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>Ciprian</hi> speaketh not here of traditions vnwritten, but of such things as the Apostles deliuered in their writinges: as the Gospels and Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, like as Paule saith: I deliuered you that I receiued of the Lorde, which thing he wrote to them. But if they will needes vnderstād him of things deliuered by the Apostles without writing: then aunswere him as <hi>Tertullian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>Origen.</hi> In obseruaunces of the church, there bee diuerse thinges whiche all men must needes doe, and yet the reason of them is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to all mē. And he reciteth in many the obseruances that <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> doth, &amp; after he concludeth: Who can certainly tell the cause of all these thinges.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunsvvere. </seg>
                  </label> The aunswere made to <hi>Tertullian,</hi> will serue <hi>Origen</hi> in this place.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>Athanasius</hi> vpon the seconde Epistle to the <hi>Thessalonians, cap.</hi> 2. vpon this place: <hi>State et tenete.</hi> Hereby it is plain, that Paul deliuered many thinges without the Scripture, not written in his Epistles, but by word of mouth only, and these are worthy no lesse fayth, then the other. Therfore I doe iudge the tradition of the church to be a thing, worthy to be credited: so that if any thing be deliuered by it, make no farther searche.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument, </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>Chrisostome</hi> in the 2. Epistle to the <hi>Thessa cap.</hi> 2. Stande fast bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and keepe the traditions &amp;c. Hereof (sayth <hi>Chrisostome</hi>) it is playne, that Paule deliuered not all thinges in his Epistles, but also many thinges without writing: and as well those, as these, are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of like faith. Wherfore we iudge the tradition of the church wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of credite: it is a tradition, searche no farther.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>Epiphanius</hi> against heresies, <hi>lib. 2. tom.</hi> 1. Againste those that call themselues Apostles, 1. <hi>cor.</hi> 11. 14. 15. We must (sayth hee) vse traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: for all thinges cannot be perceiued by the holy scripture. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:176462:34"/> the holye Apostles haue set foorth vnto vs some thinges by the word of God, and some thinges by traditions, as the Apostle sayth: as I haue deliuered vnto you, thus I teache, and thus I haue deliuered in all Churches, and thus you remember by what means I haue prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vnto you, except you haue beleeued in vayne.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunsvvere. </seg>
                  </label> Answere these iij. Authours like as <hi>Tertullian</hi> is answerered: sauing that they alleage S. Paule for their purpose, but clearely wrested from his true meaning, as it shall easily appeare to euery indifferēt Reader, that is not blinded of malice to resist the truth, as they maye plainelye perceaue by the aunswere made to S. Paule afore. And whereas they say, that things, giuen by word of mouth, are as wel to be beleeued, as those that be written: they meane that they are worthy of like credite with traditions written. For neither of both are of necessitie to salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but may be chaunged and taken away by common consente, as it is aforesayd.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Basil</hi> of the holy ghost, <hi>cap.</hi> 27. Of those doctrines that are preached in the church, we haue some deliuered vs by writing, and again, some we haue receiued by the traditions of the Apostles in misterie that is in secrete: both haue like strength to godlinesse, neither doeth anye man speake against these, whatsoeuer hee be, that hath but mean experience what the authoritie of the Churche is. For if wee (like fooles) goe about to reiect the customes of the Church, which are not written, as thinges of small waight: we shall condemne those things that be needefull for our saluation in the Gospell. Yea we shall rather cut short the true preaching of faith to bare name, and he rehearseth like traditions as <hi>Tertullian</hi> did.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ierome</hi> against the Luciferians. Although there were no authoritie of the scriptures at al, yet the consent of the whole world, in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, should haue the force of a law. For many other thinges which are obserued in the Church by tradition, haue obtained the authoritie of a law written: as to dippe the heade thrise in baptisme: and when they are christened, to giue them first pappe made of milke with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, for a signification of their infancie: on the Sonday, and on Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son weeke, not to kneele at their prayers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Augustine</hi> vpon the words of <hi>Basil.</hi> Some of the ecclesiasticall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution we haue receaued by writings: some through traditiōs from the Apostles, approued by succession: and some vse hath allowed, being strengthned by custome. Vnto al which like vsage and like af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of Godlinesse is due, of which who will doubt, though hee haue but small experiences in the scriptures? For if we set our minde
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:176462:35"/> to regarde lightly customes of the church, deliuered vs from our el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders without the scriptures: it shall easily appeare to them that looke earnestly thereon, how great losse Christian religion shall suffer. And he reciteth the same that <hi>Ierome</hi> doth, with diuerse other.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunsvvere. </seg>
                  </label> These iij. Authors, and all that make for the same purpose, be aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered before in <hi>Tertul.</hi> For not one of those thinges, that they make mention of, are necessary for our saluation: and many of thē are now taken away, and the rest, which yet remaine (as to dip the child thrise wholy in the water, to hallow the water, oile, &amp; creame: or to crosse it in the forehead) are not of necessitie to saluation. For <hi>Iohn</hi> baptised in <hi>Jordan,</hi> and the Chamberlaine of the Queene of <hi>Aethiopia</hi> was chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stened in the common streame, and children in danger of life ar chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stened of the midwife, or some other woman, without any of these ceremonies: &amp; yet they will not denie that al these baptisms be good and allowed of God. In <hi>Spaine</hi> also they dippe the childe but once as it was decreede in the Councell of <hi>Tollet.</hi> And I am sure, they wil not say that all the <hi>Spaniardes,</hi> so many yeares, haue wanted a thing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie to saluation in their Baptisme. God also regardeth not our outward bodily gesture in our prayers: but he beholdeth the fayth &amp; earnest desire of the hart of him that prayeth, whersoeuer he prayeth, and whatsoeuer his outward bodily gesture be.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>
                  </label> The same against <hi>Cresconia</hi> Gramarian, <hi>lib. 1. cap. 33. to.</hi> 7. Although we haue no certaine exāple of this matter in the canonical scriptures: yet neuerthelesse, the truth of the same scriptures in this matter is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of vs, when we do that, the whole Church alloweth. Whiche church the authoritie of the scriptures commende. And for as much, as the holy scripture can deceiue no man: who so feareth to be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with any darke speaking of it, let him aske counsell at the church therin, which without any doubt the holy scripture doth shew.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunsvvere. </seg>
                  </label> The aunswere is easie. <hi>Austen</hi> was more circumspecte, then to thinke that any doctrine might be proued by vse &amp; custome without the scripture. For baptisme of infants he bringeth in this text, except a man be born again of water &amp; the holy ghost, he cannot be my disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And because the Donatists (like as the Anabaptists do now) wrest this to them, that be of yeares of discression: against this exposition, he alleageth the maner of the Church in Christning of Infantes.</p>
               <p>By the whiche hee prooueth, that the Churche hath alway taken this sentence: excepte a man be borne againe, to be spoken also of infantes. What maner of argument should this be of <hi>Austen?</hi> The expositiō of the scripture, &amp; the vse of the sacraments, may be iudged
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:176462:35"/> by the custome vsed in the holy Church alway: Ergo the church may make a newe sacrament, and ordaine any newe Article of our fayth without the Scripture. By the sentences before cited of <hi>Austen</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, it may be easily iudged. I also graunt that euery exposition of the Scripture, wherein soeuer the old holy and true Church did agree is necessary to be beleeued. But our controuersie here is, whether any thing ought to be beleeued of necessity, without the Scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>
                  </label> The same againste the Epistle of <hi>Fundament Cap. 5. Tomo.</hi> 6. I would not beleeue the Gospel, but that the authoritie of the Church moueth me. Ergo (say they) whatsoeuer the Church sayth, we must needes beleeue them, as well as the Gospell. This Argument is naught. For the testimonie of the Church is but as a publicke office of a record, as the Exchequer, the court of the Rolles, the office of a Recorder, or a register of all Christendome: in which office men may search and haue, of the keepers, of such offices, the true copies of such lands, or other moueables, as be due to them by the law. And yet may neither the Registers, Recorders, Stewards of courts, or towne clearks put to, or take away any thing from the first original writings, no nor the iudge himselfe.</p>
               <p>But all thinges ought to be iudged by those writings. So likewise we beleeue the holy Canon of the Byble, because that the Primitiue Church of the Apostles, and eldest wryters, and nexte to their time, approoued them in their Register: that is in their wrytinges, whiche partely saw them, and partely heard them of the Apostles. And more receaue we not, because these old Fathers of the first Churche testifie in their bookes, that there was no more then these required to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued as the Scripture of God. And yet were these writinges no lesse true, afore they were alowed by them, then since, Christ witnessing &amp; saying: I seeke no witnesse of man.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>Austen</hi> to <hi>Cassulane.</hi> In these thinges, wherein the Scripture of god hath determined nothing, the custome of the people, and our el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ordinances, ought to be holden as a law: and the transgressors of the customes of the Church are likewise to be punished, as the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Gods lawe.</p>
               <p>Of which things if thou wilt dispute, and reproue one custome by another: there shall arise an endlesse strife. He repeteth also this sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence many times: that whatsoeuer is vniuersally obserued and not written in the Scripture, nor ordained by generall councels: is a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition come from the Apostles.</p>
               <p>Aunswere him as <hi>Tertullian:</hi> yet of all other authours he is moste
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:176462:36"/>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunsvvere. </seg>
                  </label> plain that nothing is of necessitie to saluation, besides the Scriptures of God, but let vs graūt for their pleasures, that those customes which they speake of, be traditions Apostolike: yet they bee no longer nor otherwise to be obserued, then the traditions Apostolike written. Which as is before fully prooued, maye (and are alreadie) bee both chaunged, and clearely taken away. And as concerning custome, it is plainely prooued, that it is not to be receaued againste the Scripture, truth or reason.</p>
               <p>They say moreouer, that the perpetuall virginitie of our Lady is to be beleeued of necessitie, as <hi>Ciprian, Chrisostome, Ierome, Ambrose, Austen,</hi> &amp; all other speaking thereof say. But this is not founde in the Scripture: Ergo there is some thing to be beleeued that is not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunsvvere. </seg>
                  </label> The Minor, that is to say, that this is not writen in the Scripture, is false. For first none of the old authours, that rehearce traditions of the Apostles vnwritten, make mention of the perpetuall virginitie of our Lady, to be one of them: but they rehearce only diuerse ceremonies, or bodily gestures, and such rites vsed in Baptisme, prayers, holy daies and fastings, which (as I haue manifestly declared) are not necessarie to saluation. But the most part of them are clean taken away, and the contrarie commaunded, and vsed by the vniuersall Church. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all the sayd Authours prooue her perpetuall virginitie by this text of Scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 44. This doore shall be still shut, and not opened for anye man to go thorow it; but only for the Lorde God of Israell, yea hee shall goe thorow it, else shall it be shut still. For if these and suche o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fathers, had not iudged her perpetuall virginitie to haue bene written in the scriptures: they woulde neuer haue iudged it to haue bene a thing to be beleeued vnder payne of damnation.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Jerome</hi> also calleth <hi>Heluidium</hi> a rash, and an vngodly man: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause that he taught, that our Lady had other children by Ioseph af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Christs birth, whiche doctrine he could not prooue by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God. In like maner we call all thē, that preache any doctrine in the Church without the authoritie of Gods word, both vngodlye, rashe, and wicked members of Antichrist.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>
                  </label> Yet they bring foorth to maintaine their error the Baptisme of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes, whiche (they saye) is not contained in the scriptures: and yet this is to be obserued vpon paine of damnation of the sayd children, Ergo there is somthing to be done of necessitie to our saluation, that is not contained in the Scriptures.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:176462:36"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunsvvere. </seg>
                  </label> Oh what a gappe these men open both to the Donatistes and to the Anabaptistes, that denie the baptising of Infantes. For if it were not written in the worde of God, no man ought to beleeue it or vse it. And so the Donatistes and Anabaptists doctrine were true, and ours false. But in deede the baptisme of Infantes is prooued by the playne Scriptures. First by the figure of the olde law, which was circumcisiō. Infants in the olde law were circumcised: Ergo in the new lawe they ought to be baptised. Againe: Infantes pertaine to God, as it is sayde to <hi>Abraham</hi> I will be thy God, and the God of thy seede after thee.<note place="margin">Gene. 17.</note> Christ sayth also: suffer childrē to come to me, for of such is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen. And again: see that ye despise not one of these little<note place="margin">Math. 19.</note> ones: for their Aungels in heauen alwayes behold the face of my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is in heauen: for the sonne of man is come to saue that,<note place="margin">Luke. 19. 1. Cor. 7.</note> that is lost. And again Paule sayth, that your children are holy nowe. By these and many other plaine wordes of scripture it is euident, that the Baptisme of infantes is grounded vppon the holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>
                  </label> Furthermore the Churche (saye they) hath chaunged the Sabboth day into the sonday, which Sabboth was commaunded by God, and neuer man found fault thereat. Seing then that the Churche had au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to chaunge Gods lawes: muche more it hath authoritie to make new lawes necessarie to saluation.</p>
               <p>There be two partes of the Sabaoth day. One is the outward bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily rest from all maner of labour and worke: and this is meere cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall, and was taken awaye with other sacrifices and ceremonies by Christ at the preaching of the Gospell. The other part of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both day is the inward rest or ceassing from sinne from our own wils and lusts, and to do only Gods will and commaundementes.</p>
               <p>Of this part speaketh the Prophet <hi>Esai.</hi> He, that takeeth heed that he vnhallow not the Sabboth day, is he, that keepeth himselfe that he<note place="margin">Esay. 56.</note> doe no euil: and they that hold greatly of the thing that pleaseth me, and keepe my couenant, vnto them will I giue an euerlasting name, that shall not perish. And moreouer the same Prophet sayth: If thou turne thy feete frō the Sabboth, so that thou doe not the thing, which<note place="margin">Esay. 58.</note> pleaseth thy selfe in my holy day: Then shalt thou be called vnto the pleasaunt, holy, and glorious Sabboth of the Lorde, where thou shalt be in honour, so that thou doe not after thine owne imaginations, neither seeke thine own will, nor speake thine owne wordes. Then shalt thou haue thy pleasure in the Lord, which shall carrie thee high aboue the earth, and feede thee with the heritage of Iacob thy father: for the Lordes owne mouth hath spoken it. This spirituall Sabboth,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:176462:37"/> that is to abstaine from sinne and to doe good, are all men bound to kepe all the dayes of their life, &amp; not only on the Sabboth day. And this spirituall sabboth maye no man alter nor chaunge, no not the whole church. That the vtter obseruing of the Sabboth is mere cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall, S. Paule writeth plainely: as that the holy dayes of the newe Moone, and of the Sabboth days are nothing but shadowes of things<note place="margin">To Ianuary epist. 119.</note> to come.</p>
               <p>And that the outward bodily rest is a meere ceremoniall precept.<note place="margin">The bodily rest on the sabboth day is figuratiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be kepte.</note> S. Austen also affirmeth, saying that among all the ten commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, this only, that is spoken of the sabboth, is commaunded figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiuely: but all the other commaundements we must obserue plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as they be commaunded, without any figuratiue speeche.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jerome</hi> also to the Galathians 4. according to the same, sayth: Lest the congregatiō of the people, without good order, should diminish the fayth in Christ: therefore certayne dayes were appointed, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we should come togither, not that that day is holier, then the other in which we come togither: but that whatsoeuer daye we assemble in, there might arise greater ioy by the sight of one of vs to another.</p>
               <p>But he that will aunswere wittily to the question prouided, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth<note place="margin">To the perfecte Christian al daies be like and euery day is goodsry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, euery day is Easter day, and vve eate his flesh alvvayes.</note> all the dayes to be like, and not that Christ is crucified only on good Friday and riseth only on the sonday: but that euery day is the day of the Lords resurrection, and we eate his flesh alwayes. But fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinges and comminges together, were ordained of wise men for thē that giue themselues rather to the worlde then to God: that cannot, yea for them that wil not come there at all, there to make their sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of prayers to God, in the face of all the people.</p>
               <p>Hereby you may easily perceaue, that the Church hath not chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the speciall part of the Sabboth, which is to cease from vice and sinne: but the ceremonial part of the Sabboth only, which was abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, and taken away with other ceremonies of Moses law, by Christ at the ful preaching of the gospel. In place wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the church hath ordained the sonday for causes aforesayd.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:176462:37"/>
               <head>The Papistes Obiections, with aunsweres vnto them. CAP. XI.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey boast themselues moreouer of the certainetye of their doctrine, and prooue it to bee true by the long continuaunce thereof, and luckie prosperitie of their Kingdome: and their aduersaryes do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to bee false, by the persecutions, plagues, miseryes, and afflictions, which they daylye suffer for theire doctrines sake.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunsvvere. </seg>
                  </label> If the triall of true Religion shoulde rest vpon antiquitie of time, or vpon worldly prosperitie: thē should the Gentils and Pagans, haue a great aduauntage of vs Christians: &amp; their religion should be better then ours, by the testimonies of our owne Scriptures. For Idolatrie and worshipping of false Gods, and their Images, was vsed long before the lawe of God, written and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to <hi>Moses,</hi> in which errors and Idolatrie the heathen continue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this day, in great prosperitie &amp; wealth vnder most victorious Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours and Princes: whereas the true Churche of Christ hath bene most miserably afflicted, from time to time: first vnder the <hi>Aegiptiās,</hi> after by the <hi>Philistines, Cananites, Pharesites, &amp;c.</hi> then by the <hi>Babilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Assirians, Mede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Persians, Sirians,</hi> and <hi>Romanes,</hi> both subdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, conquered and led away captiues. And last of all (by the Turke &amp; the Pope, the two hornes of Antichrist) the true church of Christ hath bene most cruelly persecuted vnto death, with prison, famine, water, fire, fagot, and sworde, these vij. or viij. yeares last past. Whiche Turke and Pope, although they be mortall enimies the one to the other, yet as <hi>Herode, Pilate,</hi> the Bishops, Scribes and Phariseis, although they were vtter foes eche to other, cōspired against innocent Christ, cause<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse condemning him to death on the crosse. In like maner, I say, the Pope and the Turke doe fully agree in this one poynt, to persecute &amp; murther Christe in his faithfull members. For as the sonne cannot be without his brightnesse, nor the fire without his heate, so can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:176462:38"/> the true church of god, be long without the crosse of persecution, as witnesseth S. Paule: all they that will liue godly in Iesus Christ shall suffer persecution. And our sauiour Christ saith plainly, that his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is not of this world.</p>
               <p>For if they persecute me (saith he) they shal also persecute you: and<note place="margin">Christes bage.</note> christ giueth not to his apostles earthly peace in this world, but peace and quietnesse of conscience, ioyned with persecution. For if the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked persecuted Christ himselfe, shall they not also persecute his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes? And if they so handled Christ, being the liuely tree, what thinke you shall they doe to vs, his withered braunches? And as the true Church of Christ, can neuer be long with out persecution: in like maner can the false Church of Sathan, and Antichriste, neuer ceasse from persecuting, as it appeareth througheoute the Histories of the whole Bible. Of the tirranie, and cruelty of Antichrist in persecuting of Christes true Church, prophesied <hi>Daniel</hi> long before: speaking of<note place="margin">Dani. 7.</note> the Empire and Regiment of <hi>Rome.</hi> The 4. beast (saith he) shall bee<note place="margin">The marke to knovv antichrist by, is to preuaile (by persecution) against Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecte sainctes, daniel. 8. and the marke of the true church is to be persecuted of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriste.</note> the 4. Kingdome, which shall be greater then all other Kingdomes: it shall deuour, tread downe and destroye all other landes, hee shall speake wordes against the highest of all, he shall destroy the Sainctes of the moste highest, and think that he can change times and lawes: and againe he sayth of <hi>Antiochus,</hi> which was a figure of Antichrist: there shall arise a King vnshamefaste of face, he shalbe wise in darke speaking, he shalbe mighty and strong, but not in his owne strength, he shall destroye aboue measure, and all that hee goeth aboute shall prosper in his hand: his heart shall be proude, he shall slay the strong and holy people, and through his craftinesse falsehead shall prosper in his hand, and many one shall he put to death in his welthines: hee shal stand vp against the Prince of Princes, but he shalbe slaine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hand. Of the tirrany and prosperous successe of antichrist in slay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Sainctes of God, and the reward of them that be slayne for the witnesse of Gods truth, speaketh also saincte <hi>Iohn</hi> in the. 6. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his <hi>Apocalips,</hi> vnder the opening of the foure &amp; fiue seales: and<note place="margin">Read the places.</note> in the 17. chapter, he liuely setteth forth the Pope in his own colours, vnder the person of the whoore of <hi>Babilon,</hi> being dronken with the bloud of sainctes: pointing as it were with his finger who this whore of Babilon is, and the place where she shall raign, saying: the woman, which thou sawest, is that greate citie, which reigneth ouer the kinges of the earth. Now what other citie reigned at that time or at any time since vnder the Christian kinges of the earth, but onely <hi>Rome?</hi> Whereof it foloweth <hi>Rome</hi> to bee the seate of Antichrist, and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:176462:38"/> the Pope to be very Antichrist himselfe. I could prooue the same by many other scriptures, olde writers &amp; strong reasons. But for as much as <hi>Rodulphe Gualter</hi> hath written hereof a notable worke in Latine, and now of Latine translated in to English by <hi>I. O.</hi> I remit the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to his booke, wherin he may be fully satisfied hereof. Of the pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie and securitie, that the false Church hath in worldly pleasures, vsing the same with all greedinesse and voluptuousnesse of carnall lustes, with the wicked deuices of tirannie against Christ and his true members, wherewith the vngodly daylye persecute &amp; murther gods elect for his truth, with the rewarde also of them that suffer for the same truths sake: it is most plainly written in the 2. and 3. Chapters<note place="margin">Read the chapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> of the booke of wisedome.</p>
               <p>By these Scriptures now rehearced it appeareth moste playnelye, that worldly prosperitie of the Pope and his Cleargie prooue not the truth of their doctrine: nor yet persecution of Gods true Preachers, &amp; other faithful people, argueth their doctrin to be false. But if thou wilt needs know where the true church of Christ is &amp; where the false, and not be deceiued: herein take this for a plaine and full answere, that wheresoeuer the worde of God is truely preached without addition of mans doctrines &amp; traditiōs, &amp; the sacramēts duly ministred accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Christs institution, there is the true church, the very spouse of God Christ being the head thereof. But how many, and who of that number, that heare the word of God, and receiue the sacraments, be gods elect and church, &amp; true mēbers of Christ, is known to God on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For the Lord knoweth who be his, and no man can tel, of an other man, whether he be worthie loue or hatred, although their workes seeme neuer so holy &amp; glorious afore mē, so great a witch is ipocrisie.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>
                  </label> Last of all to make all cock sure, and to maintaine their Idolatrie beside, yea and also contrarie to the word of God, as inuocation and praying to saints, worshipping of Images and Reliques, with pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, and offrings and the sacrifice of the masse, for the quicke and the dead, and pardons to deliuer dead mens soules from purgatorie, holy bread, holy water, ashes, palms, and such other bagguage: they alleage reuelations of Aungels, of our Lady and other saints, &amp; dead mens soules appearing to diuers men and women, bidding them to cause certaine masses, trentals, pilgrimages, and offring to Images &amp; reliques, of this and that Saint, to be done for them, and they shoulde be deliuered from the fire of purgatorie, where the paines be greater (say they) than mans wit can comprehend. And when suche masses, pilgrimages with offeringes to Saintes reliques and Images be done
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:176462:39"/> for them, they appeare to the same persons againe, sayinge, that by such means they be deliuered our of purgatory into the eternal ioyes of heauen: they tell also of many wonders and straunge miracles, to prooue their doctrine, in all these aforesaid thinges, to be true. And because they haue great profit and aduauntage thereby, they (coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting gaines Godlynesse) haue filled all their bookes with such vany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and lyes: of which some be so fond, and so directly against Gods glory, that the moste earnest papistes (hauing either learning or wit) be ashamed of them. Yea and the Pope himselfe hath cleane put thē out of Gods seruice, vsed in the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> and yet must wee read them, beleue them as necessary articles of our faith, or else burne therfore like heretickes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ansvvere. </seg>
                  </label> By them manifest and plaine words of the scriptures, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent of the moste ancient authors before witten, it is euident, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the visions of Angels, aparitions of the dead, nor miracles nor all these together ioyned in one, are able or sufficent to make any one new article of our faith, or stablish any thing in religion, without the expresse wordes of God: because that all such things (as is before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) may be, yea and haue bene (through Gods permission for oure sinnes and vnbelefes sake) done by the power of the diuel himselfe, or fained and counterfeited of his liuely members, Monkes, and Fryers, with other such hipocrites.</p>
               <p>But what shall Sathan neede to tel oracles, vse visions, shew appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risions, or worke miracles now adaies? what should he neede to toile herein himselfe? or why shoulde he not, like a gentleman, take his ease in his inne? seeing his subtil seruauntes, Monkes, Fryers, Nonnes and other Pope holy hipocrites, can and doe counterfeit such thinges dayly, and from their beginning hath done diligently: parte where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I shall rehearse. About fourtene yeares paste at <hi>Orleance</hi> in <hi>Fraunce</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn Sleydan.</note> the Prouostes wife died, willing to be buried at the Friers in the same city, without pomp or other solēnity cōmonly vsed at burials, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the friers, fearing to lose a great pray, if this shold be suffred to en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter into the heads of the people, caused a yōg Frier to speak in a vaut in a womans voice, many people hearing it: and said that she was the soule of the Prouostes wife, condemned in hell for contemning of the suffrages of the holy Church, cōmanding also her body to be cast out of Christian buriall. But the Prouost so bolted out the matter, that the yong frier cōfessed the place and the maner of his speking: &amp; al the friers were opēly punished for that fault in the cōmō market at <hi>Orle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</hi> But let vs come home to our own realme of <hi>England.</hi> About 30.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:176462:39"/> yeres past in the borders of <hi>Wales,</hi> within a Priory called <hi>Limster,</hi> ther was a yong woman called the holy maide of <hi>Limster,</hi> which, as the fame was, liued only by Angels foode, &amp; was enclosed within a grate of yron. Vnto whō certain days whē the Prior of the place said masse, the third part of the Ost went hanging in the aire (by miracle, as it se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) from the aulter, where the Prior massed into the maids mouth: which thing brought the people into a great opinion of holinesse in her, &amp; caused great pilgrimage to be there vsed. But whē the Lord of <hi>Burgauēny</hi> with his brother sir <hi>Edward Neuel</hi> &amp; diuerse other gētle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men &amp; Gentlewomen came to trie the truth hereof: they caused the doore to be opened, &amp; straigthwayes the dogs fought for bones, that were vnder her bed, whervpon they searching farther, found a priuie doore, whereby the Prior might resort to her and she to him, at their pleasures: &amp; then she confessed that she made (as it were) two fine threads of her own heares singly tied together with fine knots: and then made a big hole with a bodkin, through the corner of a quarter of the Ost, &amp; fastned one end of the sayd heare to the corporas, where the said Prior said masse, and the other end to her own bedde, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in she lay, and tied the other heare fast to the quarter of the Ost, and wrapped the other ende about her owne finger. And when the Prior had receiued his portion of the Ost, she wond vp the thread (whereto the host was tied) vpon her fingers, and so conueyed the Ost into her mouth. This both the Prior and she confessed, and did open penance for the same. To Saint Albans, about xxviij. yeares past came a maid creeping vppon her knees and leaning vppon two shorte staues en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring after Saint Albans bones, affirming that she should be made whole and go vprighte, so soone as shee should come to the place where Saint Albans bones were. In token whereof an Angell hadde deliuered her a key, whereby she should certainly knowe where his very bones were. And when shee passed thus through the streates of Sainte Albans creeping on her knees till shee came to Saint Albans Shrine, after she had made her prayers deuoutly there, shee tooke out the key of her purse, which shee sayd an Angell had deliuered to her: and then she stood vp right, and opened the shrine with the said key, &amp; thē kneeled again to pray, &amp; to giue thankes to God, &amp; saynt Alban for her healing &amp; giuing her strēgth to walk, which was born lame. And by &amp; by the Monks would haue had it rong for a miracle, but some wiser mē thought it meet to trie the matter better, &amp; to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin her farther, before they begā to ring a miracle openly. And vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her examination, she said that shee had bene lame from hir birth,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:176462:40"/> declaring both her kindred and place where she was borne.</p>
               <p>Vpon which confession she was cōmitted to a Nōnerie called Sop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel, there to tarrie vntill messengers, which they straight waye sente foorth, might return and testifie the truth. And so she daily and holily visited S. Albans shrine. But the night before the returne of the mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sengers she was conueyed a way and neuer heard of nor seene after. And the messengers declared to be lies all that euer she had sayd: for there was neuer none borne lame, nor none of her name, where shee sayd she was borne.</p>
               <p>A straunge thing it is to heare of the wonderfull traunces &amp; visiōs of Mistres <hi>An Wentworth</hi> of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> which tolde many men the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of their harts, which they thought no man could haue tolde but God only: she cut stomagers in peeces and made them whole again, and caused diuerse men that spake against her delusions, to go starke mad. All which thinges were prooued and openlye by her confessed to be done by Necromancie and the deceit of the deuill.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Elizabeth Barton,</hi> called the holy mayd of Courtop streate in<note place="margin">Elisabeth barton.</note>
                  <hi>Kent,</hi> passed al other in diuelish deuises. For she could (when she list)<note place="margin">O diuilishe illusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> faine her selfe to be in a traunce, disfigure her face, drawe her mouth awry toward the one eare, faining that she was thus tormēted of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than for the sinnes of the people, and deliuered frō his power by our blessed Lady of Courtop streat, and by her lead into heauen, hell, and<note place="margin">Read more of her in her booke set foorth in print and in Halles cronicle.</note> purgatorie: and there saw all the ioyes and paines of those places, &amp; tooke vpon her to prophesie of things to come, &amp; of the Kings death. This instrument of the deuill drue into her confederacie both of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie and treason, holy monkes of the Charterhouse, obstinate (they would be called) obseruant Friers of Greenwich, nice Nons of Sion, black Monkes (both of coules and condicions) of Christs church and Saint Austins of Canterburie, Knights, Squiers, learned men, Priestes, and many other: of which sort (whether they were blinded by her or else of their own meere malice &amp; hipocrisie dissēbled the matter) some, by due proofe made against thē, were iustly condemned, both of heresie and treason, and suffred with the sayde <hi>Elizabeth Barton,</hi> according to their demerites: and some acknowledging their owne offences, were deliuered by the Kinges pardon. This wicked woman<note place="margin">A letter forged as though it had come from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</note> caused a letter to be made by a Monke of S. Austins of Canterbury in golden letters, feigning the same to be deliuered to her by an Angell from heauen. This monster was cōuented both before <hi>W. Warham,</hi> Archbishop of <hi>Canterburie,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Wolsey</hi> Cardinall and Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of <hi>Yorke.</hi> Who either because that generation of the Cleargie
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:176462:40"/> hath alway defended Idolatry and superstition, or because she knew<note place="margin">Bihsops euer haue been bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterers of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</note> to much of their incontinencie and other wickednesse of liuing (for she threatned them with eternall damnation, except they repented &amp; amended their liues) they clearely discharged her without finding of any faulte in her at all. But when the matter came to be examined by <hi>Thomas Cra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mer,</hi> Archbishop of <hi>Canterburie,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> then maister of the Rolles: they so handled the matter, that they found out the whole neast of that conspiracy: wherein was disclosed the whole number of those confederates, their bookes of heresie and treason, the authours and writers of the same, and of the letter feined to be sent from heauen. All whose detestable factes, as well of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, heresy and also of treason, were so wittily and learnedly by Gods word conuinced at <hi>Canterbury</hi> by Doctor <hi>Heath,</hi> now Chanceler of <hi>Englande,</hi> (she being present and openly confessing the same) and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so by another lerned man at Pauls Crosse: that the most part of them, whiche were before by her seduced, did then vtterlye abhorre her shamelesse and abhominable facts. What a crafty poynte of legerde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine was playd about the beginning of King <hi>Edwardes</hi> reigne by a<note place="margin">A notable mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle.</note> Priest? which being at masse pricked his owne finger and caused it to drop vpō the Ost, perswading the people that the Oste bled of it selfe by the miraculous working of god, for to make the world beleue the body of Christ to be as really and natuarlly in the sacramēt, as he was born of the virgin <hi>Mary</hi> his mother. For the which heinous fact, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued against him and also by him confessed, he did open penaunce at Pauls Crosse. I wil rehearse one sermon, made in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning by a momish monke, and so leaue off their vaine and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked lies. A new vpstart preacher, being somtime a monk of Christes Church in <hi>Canterbury,</hi> stept into the pulpit in saint Pauls Church, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Christ proued re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the hoste by tvvo horses, the deuil spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in one of them.</note> that the very body of Christ is really &amp; naturally in the sacrament of the aulter: yea by Gods body is it, quoth he: &amp; because that neither oth nor periury can prooue a good argument, hee prooued the same by three notable miracles. The first of an horse, refusing to eate wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers so long, as their cakye God was among them: the second by the deuil speakīg in likenes of an horse, being cōiured of a priest by gods body to tel what he was: and the third a maide of <hi>Northgate</hi> parish in <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who he said in pretence to wipe her mouth kept the oste in her handkircher. And when she came home, she put the same into a pot close couered &amp; spitted in an other pot: &amp; after a few daies she, looking in the one pot, found a little young prety babe, about a shaft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond long, and the other pot was full of gored blood. Here is goodly
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:176462:41"/> pulpit matters to proue new articles of our faith: for if the priests that told the story of the 2 horses, or the maid that said the bread was tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a little child, or the mōke, that preached these shamful blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, or the diuel hīself, who is father of lies could lie, speaking in the horse, or in any of thē: thē do al these foresaid miracles proue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing his purpose. But O merciful God, in what a miserable state wer we thine afflicted mēbers, if it were true, which they say, being both enemies to thee &amp; to vs also for thy truths sake? For we wold not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly suffer extreme miseries, as losse of our goods, good names, and the cōpany of our dere friends in our natiue coūtrie: but also burn as he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks in this world if we came in their cruel hādling, &amp; also burn e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternaly in the vnquēchable fire of hel, if their cruel curses might take effect. Wherfore we yield thee most hartie thāks, O father of al mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, &amp; to thy son Iesus Christ our sauiour, whiche hast promised for his sake, &amp; in his name thy kingdome of heauē to al thē, which suffer persecutiō for thy righteousnesse sake. How shal we then know true visiōs of Angels, frō false, true apparitiōs &amp; miracles, frō counterfeit, but by the scripture of God, which is the rule, &amp; true measure, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we must trie al things, as S. <hi>John</hi> saith: beleeue not euery spirite, but proue thē whether they be of God. For many false Prophets are gon out into the world. Hereby is the spirit of God known, saith he: euery spirite which cōfesseth that Iesus Christ is come in the flesh, is of god, &amp;c. Whosoeuer therfore saith, that there is any thing that pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifieth the wrath of God or obtained his fauor &amp; forgiuenesse of sins but only Christs death &amp; passiō: he denieth Christ to be come a saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in the flesh. Wherfore these Angels, saints, souls of the dead, and miracles that alow worshipping of saints by inuocatiō &amp; praying to thē, the sacrifice of the masse for the quick &amp; the dead, worshipping of Images, pilgrimages, offrings to holy reliques, to forgiue sinnes or to deliuer the dead out of purgatorie: denie Christ to be come an on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sauiour by his flesh. For they make all these to be sauiours frō pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, or at the least, coadiutors to help him in that office of saluatiō &amp; deliuering those soules frō sin &amp; the pains due for the same: and so they cannot be of God but of Antichrist. Thus I haue plainly, fully &amp; truly without fraud of clokīg, or colour of rhethorike &amp; dark speech, to blind the eyes of the simple people, answered to al (that I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) which the Papists doe or can alleage, either by writing, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching or reasoning, for the defēce of their vnwritten verities, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpō they build so many detestable idolatries &amp; heresies: &amp; the same answers, if they be aptly applied &amp; placed by a discreet &amp; witty rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:176462:41"/> wil suffice for the answere to al that euer they haue or can bring forth for the maintaining of their vnwritten and vncertaine verities. And yet I will not be so much wedded to mine own wit or will, but that if they be able to answer so plainly &amp; truly to the scriptures, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors &amp; reasons rehearsed by me, as I haue done to theirs, &amp; to proue their doctrine of vnwritten verities by as plain consent both of scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, auncient doctors, and as pithie argumēts as I haue done mine, and set it foorth in print to the iudgement of the whole worlde, as mine is: I shal not only acknowledge mine ignorance and error, but I shal gladly return into <hi>England,</hi> recāt mine heresies, opēly submit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting my self to such discipline &amp; correctiō, as they shall think meete for mine offences. But if they refuse to answere my booke by writing &amp; vsing their old trade burn both my booke and the Readers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: let them know they shal do nothing but cut of the head of Hidra. For, for euery heretike (as you cal thē) which you shall burn, wil arise many faithful and constant Christians. For except the grain or corne of wheat die, it remaineth alone: but if it die, it bringeth forth muche fruite. Wherefore I most hartily beseech the father of heauen of his infinite mercie (if you be not indurate in your hearts with that sinne, which is irremissible and shall neuer be forgiuen in this world nor in the world to come, and resist the holy ghost impugning the truth of god of you knowen, &amp; defending &amp; maintaining wicked doctrines, which your consciēces beare record to be Idolatries &amp; heresies) that he wil molifie your stony harts, and giue you fleshly hearts: yea rather spiritual &amp; godly hearts to worship him truly in spirite, according to his Godly wil, expressed in his holy worde written. And I exhort all you, which feare God and bee desirous to saue your owne soules, to<note place="margin">VVhich is Rome.</note> flie from this whore of <hi>Babilon,</hi> and from al her tetestable Idolatries &amp; heresies, not building vpon the sure rocke of Gods infallible word written but vpon the quauemire of vnwritten verities: wherevpon whatsoeuer is builded foorthwith either sinketh or quite ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth. And stand thou fast and stay thy fayth, wherevpon thou shalte build al thy workes, vpon the strog rocke of Gods word written and contayned within the olde Testament and the newe: which is able sufficiently to instructe thee in all thinges needefull to thy saluation, and to the attainment of the Kingdome of heauen. To the which I beseeche the almightye Father of heauen of his infinite mercye and goodnesse, and by the merites of his onely sonne, our sauiour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demer Iesus Christ, through his onely spirit in vs bring vs all. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>